<?xml-model href="../Parker_NellNelsonProject_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
   <div type="newspaperArticle">
       <head><newspaperTitle> Chicago Times <date when="1888-07-30">Monday Morning, July 30, 1888</date>
           Price <num type="price" amount=".02">2 CENTS</num>
    </newspaperTitle>

    <seriesTitle>CITY SLAVE GIRLS</seriesTitle>

    <headLine>A <ref to="nellNelson">Lady Reporter</ref>’s Experience in the Shops with <desc
            of="workingClass">Sewing Serfs</desc>.</headLine>

    <headLine>
        <workingConditions category="wageDesc">Making Tidies at <num type="wage" amount=".60">Sixty
                Cents</num> a Dozen and Paying <num type="wage" amount="3.00">Three Dollars</num> for the
            Privilege.</workingConditions>
    </headLine>

    <headLine>
        <workingConditions category="wageDesc">A Poor Girl Who Worked from <date month="--01"
                >January</date> to <date month="--07">July</date> to make <num type="wage"
                amount="15.00">Fifteen Dollars</num>.</workingConditions>
    </headLine>

    <headLine>Making Shirts at <num type="wage" amount=".75">Seventy-Five Cents a Dozen</num> and
            <workingConditions category="negative">Finding Your Own Thread</workingConditions>.</headLine>

    <headLine>The Trials of <desc of="workingClass">Poor Creatures</desc> Who Stitch the “Never
        Rip Jersey.”</headLine></head>


    <articleBody><date when="1888-07-10">Tuesday, July 10</date>, according to instructions from <ref to="theTimes">THE
            TIMES</ref>, I made up for the role of shop-girl, and with a
        list of factories in one hand and gentle peace in the other sailed down <location type="streetName">State
            street</location> under a brown braise veil as impenetrable as an iron mask. I applied
        at two <industry>feather factories</industry> and three <industry>corset shops</industry>, but aside from the exercise up and down
        several flights of stairs got nothing. The feather people did not need any help and the
        corset folks had not started on the winter trade. <workingConditions category="positive">I was treated with civility, however, and
        given permission to “drop in a week or so.”</workingConditions> The fifth place on my list was the
            <company name="identified">“Western Lace Manufacturing Co.”</company> <location type="address">218 State street</location>. Ascending one
        flight of stairs I stopped to take off my veil and adjust my eyes to the low light. That
        done I looked about and finding a door marked ”Office of the <company name="identified">Western Lace
            Manufacturing Co.</company>” with “Come In” on the glass I complied. A <person who="workingGirl" gender="female">young girl</person>
        followed and leaving her to close the door I fell into a chair, the only one about, and
        proceeded to perspire and scrutinize the place. <workingConditions category="positive">The
            office was not uninviting. The flow had a cheap carpet, the ceiling was high and the
            room well ventilated and admirable lighted.</workingConditions> On a long table, that
        served as a sort of fortification for the private office of the company, were the
        samples—“antique crocheted good”—as they are listed, in various shades of white. All were of
        different pattern and unvarying ugliness. There were round tidies and oblong tidies, square
        mats for a bureau and smaller ones of oval and circular design, intended for a lamp or
        cushion. Behind the table, sachetiny between a writing stand and a desk, was <person gender="male">a young man of
        30 or so, of blonde type, with a stationary scowl between his eyebrows and <unclear/>
        otherwise pleasing manner. That is, I thought the manner pleasing till I began to get
        acquainted with it and then my opinion changed.</person> After a lapse of five minutes or so the
        <person gender="male">fair-haired gentlemen</person> turned to the <person who="workingGirl" gender="female">young girl</person> with a deepening of the <unclear/> and a most
        unalluring <dialogue><mascVoice>“Well?”</mascVoice>.<unclear/> <femVoice>“I brought the mate back.”</femVoice> <mascVoice connotation="negative">“Oh, you have, eh?”</mascVoice></dialogue> opening a piece
        of newspaper and unfolding a dozen hand-made mats the size of a tea-plate. <workingConditions category="negative">The work is
        carefully examined on both sides and as he proceeds the scowl deepens. Without a word he
        tosses the lot on the little table and reaches for the proffered black the girl had opened.</workingConditions>
        <dialogue><mascVoice>“What’s your name?”</mascVoice> <femVoice>“<persName>Rhafferty</persName>.”</femVoice> <mascVoice>“How do you spell it?”</mascVoice>
        <femVoice>“R-h-a-f-f-e-r-t-y.”</femVoice> <mascVoice>“Oh, yes; <persName>Martha Rhafferty</persName>,”</mascVoice> after hunting through
        a long list. <mascVoice>“Do you want more work?”</mascVoice> <femVoice>“No, sir.”</femVoice> <mascVoice>“There’s plenty more if you want it.”</mascVoice> <femVoice>“No;
        my mother don’t want me to do any more <occupation>crocheting</occupation>.</femVoice> <mascVoice>“Well, <persName>Mr. White</persName>
        isn’t in now. Can’t you come in again?”</mascVoice> No answer. A look of discouragement comes over the
        young face. <mascVoice>“Don’t you have to do any shopping about town?”</mascVoice> <femVoice>“No, sir.”</femVoice> <mascVoice>“Well, you can wait,
        can’t you? Wait here. Take a chair. (I had the only one.) Just go in the next room there and
        take a chair.</mascVoice></dialogue> As he went to lead the way <person who="forePerson">the crochet-teacher</person> called his attention, and the
        girl remaining I seized my chances for a bit of interviewing. <persName>Martha</persName> showed me her contract,
        in which <workingConditions category="wageDesc">the firm agreed to refund $1 of the $3 deposited when she had finished $15 worth of
        work</workingConditions>. On the back of the contract were the credit receipts of the company entered in lead
        pencil, dating from <date month="--01">January</date> to <date month="--07">July</date>. She told me she lived in <placeName type="general">Gross Park</placeName>, away out on the
        <location type="general">West side</location> that <desc of="workingClass">she helped her mother, and had been trying to earn <num type="wage" amount="15.00">$15</num> since <date month="--01">January</date></desc>. She
        received <workingConditions category="wageDesc"><num type="wage" amount=".60">60 cents</num> a dozen for the mats and it took her a week to crochet a dozen</workingConditions>. <dialogue><femVoice connotation="negative">“Then I
        must pay <num type="cost" amount=".10">10 cents</num> car fare each time, and that leaves only <num type="wage" amount=".40">40 cents</num>. I had to pay <num type="cost" amount="3.00">$3</num> before I
        could get any work. I always knew how to crochet, but they made me pay <num type="cost" amount="2.00">$2</num> for lessons and <num type="cost" amount="1.00">$1</num>
        as a security. I began in <date month="--01">January</date>, the first week, and now I am through. <workingConditions category="wageDesc">I have made <num type="wage" amount="15.00">$15</num>,
        and when they give me back the dollar I shall have <num type="wage" amount="16.00">$16</num>.</workingConditions>”</femVoice> <nellVoice connotation="negative">Here is a company paying a girl of
        18 $15 for six months and one week’s labor.</nellVoice></dialogue> When <persName>Mr. Ford</persName> came from the
        work-room he was met by <person>a boy</person> who had brought in some work and was in a hurry to be off.
           <dialogue><mascVoice who="boy"> “<persName>Mrs. Clark</persName> sent these mats and she, wants you to receipt for
        them.”</mascVoice> The paper is opened and the work inspected. The scowl deepens. There will be trouble
        and I prick up my ears. <mascVoice who= "forePerson" connotation="negative">“I don’t like this. This is bad. They are all stained. Are you
        her—her—are you a relation?”</mascVoice> <mascVoice who="boy">“Yes.”</mascVoice> <mascVoice who="forePerson" connotation="negative">“Well, you must tell her to wash her hands. These goods
        are all sweet. I’ll have to charge her for spoilage the material if it occurs again. Did she
        tell you to ask for more work?”</mascVoice> <mascVoice who="boy">“No, sir.”</mascVoice></dialogue> The poor boy is gone. <persName>Martha</persName> sits in the back
        room the picture of <unclear/> and the entry being made I am approached.
            <desc of="middleClass">I look like a beggar and that is what I am taken for, as, the pretty
            blonde secretary only scowls.</desc> He stands and looks down at me and I
        sit and look up at him waiting for the, lines in the handsome brow to deepen, the edge of
        the soft, brown mustache to curl, and the laconic, withering <dialogue><mascVoice>“well”</mascVoice> to break the gaze. It
        comes. <nellVoice>“Have you any work?”</nellVoice> I ask. <mascVoice>“Plenty.” Do you want work?”</mascVoice> <nellVoice>“Yes.”</nellVoice> <mascVoice>“What can you do?”</mascVoice>
       <nellVoice> “Oh, I can crochet.”</nellVoice> <mascVoice>“This kind of work?”</mascVoice> handing over one of the <num type="cost" amount=".60">60-cent</num> mats. <nellVoice>“Yes; what
        do you pay?”</nellVoice> <mascVoice>“Different prices. Pay by the dozen, from <num type="wage" amount=".60">60 cents</num> to <num type="wage" amount="10.00">$10</num>.”</mascVoice> <nellVoice>“Let me have a
        dozen of the $10 kind, please,</nellVoice></dialogue>giving my cat-colored eyes a mater doloroso sort
            of a roll
              As he caught the seraphic expression some facial machinery gave a lurch that threw on side
        of his countenance bias for a second. Reaching to the desk he pulled out the following
        circular and handed it to me. <company name="identified">OFFICE OF WESTERN LACE MANUFACTURING CO.
                (Incorporated)</company>, <location type="address">218 STATE STREET, CHICAGO,
            ILL</location>—<unclear/>: In reply to your letter regarding the work we send
        out to ladies to do at their homes we beg to say that we make a large line of crochet goods
        of our antique crochet cotton a sample of which you will find enclosed, also linen, silk,
        etc. We make <factoryItem>mats</factoryItem>, <factoryItem>tidies</factoryItem>, <factoryItem>lambrequins</factoryItem>, <factoryItem>bedspreads</factoryItem>, <factoryItem>shams</factoryItem>, <factoryItem>collars</factoryItem>, <factoryItem>hood</factoryItem>, <factoryItem>lace edging</factoryItem>, etc.,
        in large quantities. We have been established here for the last five years and have extra
        facilities for selling goods in large lost: so we are enabled to keep our workers in steady
        work all the time. Should you desire to work for us we should be pleased to send you work on
        the following terms: When you send order for work you are required to remit to us <num type="cost" amount="3.00">$3</num>: <num type="cost" amount="2.00">$2</num> of
        this is to pay us for the patterns and instructions which we shall send you with each lot of
        new work. We shall also send you sufficient extra material so you can make a sample of each
        pattern sent, which you are allowed to keep for yourself; <num type="cost" amount="1.00">$1</num> of the <num type="cost" amount="3.00">$3</num> you send is a deposit
        on the material we send, and this we shall return to you at any time when you return the
        work and wish to stop. You will be kept in steady work, paid for each lot when made and
        re-turned to us in good order. <workingConditions category="wageDesc">Our work is all made by the dozen, and prices range from <num type="wage" amount=".50">50
        cents</num> per dozen to <num type="wage" amount="10.00">$10</num> per dozen, according to amount of work. An easy pattern, with sample
        and full instructions, will be sent you at first, and the quality of work, and advance in
        prices as you adapt yourself to do-ing it. The work will be sent you by mail, post-age paid
        by us one way. Three month’s time is allowed you to do any one dozen of articles we send.</workingConditions>
        This enables ladies who have only a few hours daily to spare to do our work as well as those
        ladies who take it intending to do it steadily. We are asked many times how much a lady can
        earn. This depends entirely upon your ability to crochet and the time you have at your
        command daily; ladies earning from <num type="wage" amount="2.00">$2</num> to <num type="wage" amount="3.00">$3</num> weekly. We could not guarantee to anyone any
        stated amount that they could earn, but our work is easy and after you accustom yourself to
        it you can do it very rapidly. If you desire work for us fill out the blank be-low and
        return it to us with the <num type="cost" amount="3.00">$3</num>, and we will place your name on our books and send work at once
        with full instructions. Send your money by post-office order, draft, payable to our order,
        or registered letter at our risk. Very Truly, <company name="identified">WESTERN LACE MANUFACTURING
            CO.</company> Keep the above for future reference. …………………………………………………… …………………..188
                <company name="identified">WESTERN LACE MANUFACTURING CO.</company>, <location type="address">218 STATE
                STREET, CHICAGO, Ill.</location>—Gentlemen: In-closed find <num type="cost" amount="3.00">$3</num> that I send
        you to secure patterns, instructions, and material for crochet work; $2 is to pay you for
        samples and instructions, and <num type="cost" amount="1.00">$1</num> is for deposit on material which I shall demand returned to
        me at any time when I return to you the material in my hands. Signature………………………………………….
        Town……………………………………………… County……………………………………………. Street and No……………………………………… <dialogue><nellVoice>“What’s the <num type="cost" amount="3.00">$3</num>
            for?”</nellVoice> I ask. <mascVoice connotation="negative">“Can’t you read? The <num type="cost" amount="2.00">$2</num> is to pay for the samples and instruction and the <num type="cost" amount="1.00">$1</num> as
        a security for our material. I don’t know who you are and if I gave you the thread I might
        never see you again.” “I don’t need instruction. I can make the stitch and I don’t want to
        put any such amount in samples.</mascVoice> <nellVoice>If you can’t trust me with a spool of thread and a pattern
        will you sell me the material?”</nellVoice> <mascVoice>“That’s not the way we do business. If you want to work for
            us you will have to comply with the contract. You pay <num type="cost" amount="3.00">$3</num>; that entitles you to a sample mat
            which we teach you how to make. After you have <num type="wage" amount="15.00">$15</num> made worth of work we refund the <num type="cost" amount="1.00">$1</num>.”</mascVoice>
       <nellVoice> “What about the other $2?”</nellVoice> <mascVoice>“It goes to us for instruction and samples.”</mascVoice> <nellVoice>“Will I have to make
        the samples?”</nellVoice> <mascVoice>“Yes.”</mascVoice> <nellVoice>Then there are thirteen in the <company name="identified">Western Lace Manufacturing
            company</company>'s dozen?”</nellVoice> <mascVoice>“If you can to put it that way, yes. But you get one of each
        set.”</mascVoice> <nellVoice>“But I don’t want any. I have a supply. Tell me how much will you sell me a thirteenth
        of a dozen of this set for?”</nellVoice> <mascVoice>“The price is on the tag.”</mascVoice> <nellVoice connotation="sarcasmWit">“Ah. I see <num type="cost" amount=".15">15 cents</num>: and you pay <num type="cost" amount=".60">60
        cents</num> a dozen for making them, a profit of <num type="profit" amount="1.20">$1.20</num>. The best thing I’ve struck yet. And stock
        for sale?”</nellVoice> The scowl becomes threatening, but I venture to ask how much thread it takes to
        mat for a closer calculation of the profits. No answer is deigned. <nellVoice>“If I give you $3 you
        will give me work?”</nellVoice> <mascVoice>“Yes,”</mascVoice> in a sullen tone. <nellVoice>“How much?”</nellVoice> <mascVoice>“All you can do,”</mascVoice> brightening up a
        little. <nellVoice>“How do I know you will give me back $1 after I’ve earned $15?” I ask. “I don’t know
        anything about you. I never heard of your firm before and there is no name on this paper.”</nellVoice>
        <mascVoice>“I guess your motives are bad. You don’t want work.”</mascVoice> <nellVoice>“What guarantee have you to offer of
        honesty or respectability?”</nellVoice> With glaring eyes, distended nostrils, and face crimson with
        rage he threw down a pile of <num type="cost" amount=".02">2-cent</num> blank books in front of me. <mascVoice connotation="angry">“There’s our customers:
        every state in the union is represented; go to them if you want references. Here are more
        too.”</mascVoice> slamming down a sheet of paper with names and <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName> addresses of about forty women.
        <nellVoice>‘I see you have a minimum local trade. Chicago women don’t seem overzealous about the
        crocheting business.”</nellVoice> Then I asked him where he got a market for the goods and the name of
        some business man to whom I could go for reference. <mascVoice>“Now I am not going to do any more
        talking with you about this business.”</mascVoice> <nellVoice>“Why?? Is it a secret organization, a sort of
        Maso<unclear/>”</nellVoice> <mascVoice >“No. It isn’t secret or Ma<unclear/> either, but I don’t believe you’re all
        right and I won’t answer any more questions until I know who you are and what you want.”</mascVoice></dialogue>
        Poor <persName>Mr. Ford</persName> was so furious by this time that I thanked him for his
        attention and bade him good afternoon. At the foot of the stairs I waited to tie my veil on
        and see how <persName>Martha</persName> fared, but at the expiration of thirty minutes she
        was still waiting for <persName>Mr. White</persName> and her <unclear/>.
            <workingConditions category="wageDesc">Of the five women I interrogated none were able to earn <num type="wage" amount=".20">20 cents</num> a
            day</workingConditions>. <desc of="workingClass">All expressed a liking for the work but
            complained bitterly of the way the <unclear/> gave out the work.</desc> For
        instance <factoryItem>bedspreads</factoryItem> paid <num type="wage" amount="10.00">$10</num> a dozen, but not more than three spreads were given to a hand
        and one of these was the sample. The little <factoryItem>tablemats</factoryItem> paid <num type="wage" amount=".50">50 cents</num> per dozen, but before a
        girl was able to crochet enough to live on she was obliged to take collars made of line
        thread in such an intricate pattern that it was an utter impossibility to earn <num type="wage" amount="1.00">$1</num> a month.
       <workingConditions category="wageDesc"> No woman seen had earned <num type="wage" amount="15.00">$15</num> in less than six months, and one of the most skilled hands had
        been on a <num type="wage" amount=".60">60-cent</num> lot since <date when="1888-06-03">June 3</date>.</workingConditions> <workingConditions category="negative">By inquiry I learned that many women
            paid <num type="cost" amount="3.00">$3</num> and gave up the work when they saw it was not possible to make the <num type="wage" amount="15.00">$15</num> necessary
            for the rebate. </workingConditions> This fact does not appear in the circulars, and it
        is not <unclear/> after the contract has been signed that the <unclear/> tacties of the
        concern are understood. 
                Several cases are on record at the <orgName>Woman’s Protective
            agency</orgName>, but no judgment has been obtained, as the agreement <unclear/> valid
        be-fore the law. All that can be done in the matter is to warn the public against a
            <unclear/> legally incorporated to grind the life out of the women and girls unfortunate
            enough to patronize it.
        <headLine>CLOAKS, OVERALLS, AND SHIRTS</headLine>
        <headLine><workingConditions category="negative">Put Through an Impudent Cross-Examination to Get to Sew <factoryItem>Cloaks</factoryItem> at <num type="wage" amount=".50">50 cents</num> Each
            Making <factoryItem>Pants</factoryItem> and <factoryItem>Shirts</factoryItem> at <num type="wage" amount=".75">75 Cents</num> a Dozen and Find your Own Thread.</workingConditions></headLine> At
            <company name="identified">Rosenthal &amp; Co.’s and Rosenberg Bros</company>. I applied for work and was
        told to report in the morning to sew on <factoryItem>cloaks</factoryItem>. The manager in
            <company name="identified">Stein’s</company>, on <location type="streetName">Market street</location>, wanted bands and
        offered to engage me at once. I was most impudently catechized some seven inquires requiring
        as many false statements. What was my name, place of residence, last position, amount of
        wages received, state of my health, nativity, <dialogue><nellVoice connotation="sarcasmWit">married or single—to which I
            answered “neither.” Here was a dilemma. “Oh, yes, widow?” and
            an inordinate ha! ha!</nellVoice>
        <nellVoice>Yes.</nellVoice>
        <mascVoice connotation="negative">“Grass widow, eh?” with a sneer.</mascVoice>
        <nellVoice>How much do you pay for <factoryItem>cloaks</factoryItem>, I asked, tired of the ordeal</nellVoice>
        <mascVoice>“<num type="wage" amount=".50">Fifty cents</num>, each.”</mascVoice></dialogue> It was enough and I left the creature still anxious to solve the widow question. By the time I reached <company name="identified">Ludden’s</company>, <location type="address">122 Market
            street</location>, I was in a reckless frame of mind. <dialogue><nellVoice>“Is there any
        work for a good sewer?”</nellVoice> I asked the girl in the office. <femVoice connotation="positive">“Yes, plenty.
            <persName>John</persName> give her some pants.”</femVoice></dialogue> <persName>John</persName> had eyes the
        color of calico and a complexion like an immature tomato. He led the way to the <factoryItem>cottonades</factoryItem>,
        which were cut, trimmed, and tied up in bundles of a dozen garments each. <dialogue><mascVoice>“Here’s a sample,”</mascVoice>
        holding up a pair of <factoryItem>overalls of brown cottonade</factoryItem>. <mascVoice connotation="descriptionNeutral">“The work is cut out, but you will have to do everything yourself. I want you to make the fly extra strong and press the buttons. <workingConditions category="wageDesc">We
        pay <num type="wage" amount=".75">75 cents</num> a dozen</workingConditions> and you <workingConditions category="negative">find your own thread</workingConditions>.”</mascVoice> <nellVoice connotation="negative">“<num type="wage" amount=".75">Seventy-five cents</num> for a dozen of these
        <factoryItem>pants</factoryItem> and find my own thread?”</nellVoice> <mascVoice>“Yes. <workingConditions category="wageDesc">Or I’ll pay you <num type="wage" amount=".80">80 cents</num> a dozen and give you linen thread if you sew the buttons on fast</workingConditions>.”</mascVoice> <nellVoice>“No. I guess I won’t take the pants. What other work
        have you?”</nellVoice> <mascVoice connotation="descriptionNeutral">“Here are <factoryItem>cheviot shirts</factoryItem> if you’d rather. Gusset the tail here and the sleeves,
        stay the bosom and arm-holes, and make the collar and wrist-bands extra strong. <workingConditions category="wageDesc">These pay <num type="wage" amount=".75">75
        cents</num> a dozen.</workingConditions>”</mascVoice> He offered to give me three on trial. <workingConditions category="wageDesc">The thread would cost <num type="cost" amount=".05">5 cents</num>,
        car-fare <num type="cost" amount=".10">10 cents</num>, and I should have <num type="wage" amount=".03">3 cents</num> after the job.</workingConditions> <persName>John</persName> said:
        <mascVoice>“That’s so, but I can’t help it. If the work is satisfactory you can have a six-dozen lot.”</mascVoice>
         <nellVoice connotation="sarcasmWit">It was very good of <persName>John</persName> to sympathise with me, but I thanked him and
        said I would look a little further.</nellVoice></dialogue> <headLine>THE NEVER-RIP JERSEY.</headLine>
        <headLine>A Hard Day’s Work for <num type="wage" amount=".41">41 Cents</num>—Less Fortunate Workers Who Earned Only <num type="wage" amount=".11">11 Cents</num>—A
            Sick Girl’s Sad Story—<desc of="workingClass">The Hopeless Miss Who Longed to Be Married</desc>.</headLine> At the
                <company name="identified">Never-Rip Jersey Company</company> I was told to
        apply at the factory <location type="address">133 West Washington street</location>. “Work is given out at
        7:30 a. m.,” the clerk informed me, “and if you have any snap about you you can make a good
        living. By the way of getting the required snap I went home, ate my dinner, and was in bed
        at 8 o’ clock. <desc of="workingClass">The next morning I resumed the rags of poverty and at 7 o’clock made my debut
        as the factory hand.</desc> <workingConditions category="workDesc">I was one of 120 women, ranging in age from 15 to
            60</workingConditions>. The factory where the <factoryItem>never-rip jerseys</factoryItem> are made is
        at the <location type="streetName">corner of Washington and Union streets</location>, with the elevator
        entrance in the rear and workroom in the fifth story. The girls began to arrive at 7
        o’clock, and at every trip of the elevator some twenty or more were carried up-stairs. I
        took a chair in one of the machine rows, and for an hour did nothing but watch the
        preparations for work in that <workingConditions category="comparison">human hive</workingConditions>. <workingConditions category="negative">The room was
        50x138, with an open unfinished roof and brick walls calcimined</workingConditions>. Light was admitted from
        rear and side windows. <workingConditions category="workDesc">The pressmen had their boards and furnaces at the south end of the
        room, where all the work was pressed prior to being boxed and ticketed for the trade. At the
        extreme opposite end was the cutting-room, fenced in from the rest, and between the two were
        the worktables, where the hundred odd girls stitched and finished the <factoryItem>jerseys</factoryItem>.</workingConditions>
        Along the brick walls were nails, irregularly driven, on which the girls hung their hats and
        wraps, dresses and collars. Nearly every one took off her dress and waisit, turned it inside
        out, put it on a nail and put on a calico of old stuff shop suit. A few took off their
        corsets and nearly all the machine hands changed their shoes before work. On the stroke of
        7:30 a bell rang, the power was turned on <workingConditions category="comparison">the machines began to buzz like little saw-mills
        and the day’s work had commenced</workingConditions>. <workingConditions category="negative">Heads of brown, black, yellow, and gray bent so near the
        flying shuttles that every minute I experted the bangs and fluffy crimps would get caught in
        the machinery. </workingConditions> <nellVoice connotation="pity">The faces were sad and so very, very pales that I
                shall never look at a <factoryItem>jersey</factoryItem> again without seeing
                them.</nellVoice>
        <workingConditions category="workDesc">The average age may have been 23, but not less.</workingConditions>
        <workingConditions category="negative">There were girls of 17 and 18 and some world-weary women past 50 all
            working for little more than enough to keep body and soul together.</workingConditions>
        The work circulated in baskets—long chip hampers with stout-handles—that held a dozen, with
        room for five times that quantity. <workingConditions category="workDesc">A great deal of time was lost by the
            workers in getting the contents of the basket examined, checked off on the ticket and
            the ticket stamped.</workingConditions>
        <desc of="workingClass">If it had been the last change for life I don’t believe the girls would have worked
            any harder for salvation. Scarcely a head was raised from machine or lap.</desc>
        <nellVoice connotation="pity"><workingConditions category="negative">Shoulders were bent down, chests hollowed in, and
                faces drooped so low that I could not begin to make a study of the “windows of the
                souls” before me.</workingConditions></nellVoice> At 8:40 the proprietor of the
        chair I was in asked me to vacate, and I walked down through the narrow aisles of
            <occupation>sewing-women</occupation> to the “<person who="forePerson" gender="female">forelady</person>” and asked for work.
        She asked me if I wanted to take a machine, but I expressed a preference for finishing. I
        was given a numbers, a basket with five <factoryItem>jerseys</factoryItem> to finish, and a chair beside a
        girl named <persName>Hannah</persName>, who, being engaged by the way was told to “show me.”
            <persName>Hannah</persName> had blonde hair and talked with the brogue. <workingConditions category="workDesc">She gave me a
        needle as long as my engagement finger, and the most meager instruction compatible with
        obedience. Fortunately I had my thimble and crossing my knees I threaded the
           gimlet-like needle with silk and I proceeded to
            hook-and-eye a <factoryItem>jersey</factoryItem>.</workingConditions> Remembering the treachery of
        my shop clothes I ever wore filled the two hooks and eyes with sewing and after testing them
        proceeded to face the collar. <desc of="workingClass">I told <persName>Hannah</persName> about my misery, but she
            wisely said it was no fault of hers and went on with a <workingConditions category="wageDesc"><num type="wage" amount="3.00">$3</num>-a-dozen lot she had been doing two
        days and a half</workingConditions>.</desc> <workingConditions category="camaraderie">Thinking it would be a good way to get acquainted with my neighbors I asked
        several for a fine needle and at last exchanged the crow-bar <persName>Hannah</persName> had
        given me for a line cambric article. It worked better</workingConditions> and at the end of two
        hours I had bound the arm-holes,
           faced the collar,
            tacked the front facing and the bustle
        piece, and put two patts of hooks and eyes in a black <factoryItem>jersey</factoryItem>. <workingConditions category="negative">The
            dye was not fast, neither was the wool, for my throat, ears,
            and nostrils were tufted with black lint. I was African from the nails to the wrists.</workingConditions> The
        front facings had to be trimmed off. I had no scissors. <persName>Hannah</persName> was
        dangerous with her, and <workingConditions category="wageDesc">I lost about <num type="cost" amount=".15">15 cents</num> worth of time borrowing the weapons.</workingConditions>
               <workingConditions category="negative">At noon I had finished four <factoryItem>jerseys</factoryItem> and was
                so sore about the neck and back that I could scarcely rise from the
                chair.</workingConditions> <workingConditions category="camaraderie">I began to scent hot tea, and looking about saw
        a big girl called <persName>Emma</persName> brewing three pots of <placeName type="country">Japan</placeName> over one of the
        press furnaces. She had her front hair in curl papers and was whistling “In The Sweet Bye
        and Bye.” About thirty girls went to her, each with her own cup, for a supply of tea. I
        remarked to one passing my chair that her tea looked awfully nice and asked where she got
        it. “From <persName>Em</persName>. She makes it and we each pay <num type="cost" amount=".02">2 cents</num> a week.”</workingConditions> <workingConditions category="negative">On the
        stroke of 12 the machine stopped and 120 tired women stopped too, for thirty minutes’ rest
        and the food that could hardly be called refreshing. In the main it consisted of brown bread
        and butter. In some parcels there was cold meat and cake: others had pie; a few a bottle or
        canteen of milk, cold tea or coffee, but I did not see a particle of fruit.</workingConditions> <desc of="workingClass">One little girl
        who had been stretching <factoryItem>jerseys</factoryItem> at <num type="wage" amount=".02">2 cents</num> each made a lunch on three graham
        crackers and a piece of custard pie, which she ate reading a paper-covered book. I counted
        thirty-seven girls with a lunch of dry bread, fifteen with sandwiches, and ten who ate cold
        pancakes. Twenty-three girls were without any luncheon whatever.</desc> During the intermission the
        elevator stopped running and no one left the building but myself. Less than ten minutes was
        spent over the wretched mea. <workingConditions category="negative">At one side of the west wall, separated by a
            ten-foot pine partition, was the toilet-room containing an iron zinc with one faucet of
            running water.</workingConditions>
        <workingConditions category="comparison">Here the girls crowded like so many cattle</workingConditions>, each with her
        bit of soap and grimy cotton towel, to wash. Dress waists were loosened and necks, faces,
        arms, and hands lathered with soap and rinsed, as the change permitted. <workingConditions category="negative">There were three
        closets, unflushed, untidy, and unwholesome. Set up against the wall in this enclosure, with
        the faucet run through the partition, was a barrel of ice water inscribed in big letters:
          “Two cents will be collected every Saturday for ice
          water.”</workingConditions> <workingConditions category="negative">Besides this luxury every hand pays <num type="cost" amount=".12">12 cents</num> a week for the
        use of the machine.</workingConditions> At 1 o’clock I finished my basket, which I dragged to
            <persName>Tom</persName>, the book-keeper, who took my name and credited me with five
        garments. <workingConditions category="wageDesc">No price had been put on the <factoryItem>jerseys</factoryItem>, as they were sampled goods, but
        the forelady thought they would go at <num type="wage" amount=".60">60 cents</num> a dozen, which meant <num type="wage" amount=".25">25 cents</num> to my credit.</workingConditions> I
        didn’t get any more work till 2 o’clock because <desc of="middleClass">the <person who="forePerson" gender="female">forelady</person> was in the
        toilet-room having her bangs done up in paper. She was a pretty woman, by the way, with a
        good face and a shock of beautiful auburn hair. She had been in her position for six years
        and was drawing a salary of <num type="wage" amount="35.00">$35</num> a week. The girls had a good word for her generally, but she
        struck me as being a woman without heart.</desc> At her appearance I was given a basketful of
            <factoryItem>jerseys</factoryItem> to finish button-holes. <workingConditions category="comparison">I
            worked like a Trojan for an hour</workingConditions>, at the end of which I won the heart
        of a <person who="workingGirl" gender="female">little girl</person> who sat at the end of my table facing the wall. She had been sitting still
        so long that I called out and asked if she were ill. <femVoice connotation="negative">“No. I haven’t any work.”</femVoice>
                    <workingConditions category="negative">Tired almost to exhaustion and as
                    hot as a newly-built mustard plaster I was only too glad of a chance to transfer
                    my interests, but she declined.</workingConditions>
        It was too hot to work; she was going away soon, she said, and didn’t care to do any more.
        <femVoice connotation="woe">“When did I begin? Today. I worked in a <industry>box-factory</industry>, but it was so dull I could only earn <num type="wage" amount=".16">16
        cents</num> a day. <livingConditions category="negative">My mother wants me to pay her <num type="cost" amount="2.50">$2.50</num> a week board, but how could I with <num type="wage" amount=".96">96
            cents</num>.</livingConditions> This is no better. I came at 8 this morning and I have only made <num type="wage" amount=".11">11 cents</num>. I am 21.
        <desc of="workingClass">Beaus? Yes, some. I have on steady fellow, but I don’t know if he will marry me. I hope he
        will.</desc> She told me he earned <workingConditions category="wageDesc"><num type="wage" amount="75.00">75$</num> a month as a telegraph operator on the board of trade</workingConditions>; that
        he was “steady as a steeple, and the only fellow she ever loved.”</femVoice> <workingConditions category="camaraderie">I told her how to go about
        catching the prosperous telegrapher and rehashed a recipe given me by no less a personage
        than <persName>Mrs. John M. Sherwood</persName>, which I had never tried. She was going to a
        picnic at <placeName type="general">Garfield park</placeName> at 6 o’clock and brought over a <num type="cost" amount=".25">25-cent</num>
        chocolate cake to show me. Then she loaned me her scissors, told me good-by, and went home
        to dress for the fete.</workingConditions> <desc of="workingClass">Nothing of any importance occurred till someone passed the news that
        a girl was asleep in the closet. Half a dozen left their machines to look at her,
            <persName>Hannah</persName>, my mentor, among them. “Oh, you just ought to see her, fast
        asleep, with her mouth wide open.” It was more than I could stand.</desc> I threw my
            button-holes into the basket and went to the toiletroom.
            <desc of="workingClass"> Sure enough, there was the <person who="workingGirl" gender="female">poor girl</person> sitting in the dirty place, her
            head resting against a folded apron, breathing in the foul air that reeked with filth
            and disease. The walls of the closet were black with pencil marks,
        the floor was strewn with lint and threads, and the pale face of the sleeper looked ghastly
        in the darkness. She had tied one end of a string to the latch and the other to the drop
        chain.</desc> <dialogue><nellVoice connotation="pity">“My dear child, musnt’t sleep here. Are you sick?”</nellVoice> <femVoice>“Oh, I am so sick.”</femVoice></dialogue>
            <workingConditions category="camaraderie">Instantly there were a dozen willing hands to help her out to a window
            where a chair was placed for her. We rubbed her temples, chafed her hands, bathed her
            head, and got her some lemons.</workingConditions> After making her toilet she came over to my
        table as I sewed away at my button-holes she told me her story.
           <dialogue><femVoice connotation="woe"> “<persName>Rose</persName> and I are only six months in this country. We came from
            <placeName type="country">England</placeName> with our brother and live on <location type="streetName">Carpenter
            street</location>. The climate doesn’t agree with me and I am sick all the time. At
        first we worked in <company name="identified">Marshall Field’s</company> and <persName>Rose</persName> and I
        made fringe. <workingConditions category="wageDesc">We got <num type="wage" amount="7.00">$7</num> a week and were so happy.</workingConditions> <workingConditions category="positive">It was awful nice there. We didn’t have to
        pay for drinking water or anything; there were lots of towels, whole cakes of soap, and oh,
        it was so clean. We had a <person who="forePerson" gender="male">foreman</person> over us and he was as good as a brother to us. Sometimes
        we let our money lay and drew it in a pile; oh, such a lot as it was! We put away very much
        of it.</workingConditions> But I got sick and all we ‘ad saved went for doctor and medicine. Then the work
        stopped. They took our names though and promised to send for us in the fall. For a while we
        worked in the box factory, but liked to starve. Then we went to
            <company name="identified">Ellinger’s</company> and <workingConditions category="negative">made <factoryItem>cloaks</factoryItem> at <num type="wage" amount=".30">30 cents</num> each, but it was
        so hard, and we couldn’t please them no matter how we tried.</workingConditions> <workingConditions category="negative">We came here today, but it’s
        only a fit place to starve in. All the work they gave me was a dozen <factoryItem>jerseys</factoryItem> to
        button; that’s <num type="wage" amount=".11">11 cents</num> a row; had two dozen holes to finish at <num type="wage" amount=".16">16 cents</num>. <num type="wage" amount=".27">Twenty-seven cents</num>
        for the two of us! How can we live on it?</workingConditions>”</femVoice> and the child began to cry again. <nellVoice connotation="pity">By way of
        comforting her I took her name, promised to help her, and gave her my check for <num type="wage" amount=".41">41 cents</num>.</nellVoice>
        She didn’t think it would be honored so I took it to the cashier myself and demanded pay as
        I was not coming back in the morning. <mascVoice>“No, ma’am,” said <persName>Tom</persName>, “you don’t
            get it. Come round on the <date day="---20">20th</date> and I hunt you up.”</mascVoice></dialogue> At 5:30 work ceased. <workingConditions category="workDesc">Each girl had to
        sweep out her place, clean and oil the machine, and return her basket and check.</workingConditions> I paid a
        nickel to have my corner swept, and finding it impossible to wash up sans towel and soap I
        got under my veil and rang the elevator. The pressers laughed and told me to try the
        stairs—five flights. Down I went. At the second I went into the salesroom to buy a
            <factoryItem>jersey</factoryItem>. One of the firm waited on me; his magnanimity was sublime.<nellVoice connotation="sarcasmWit"> The
        identical black <factoryItem>jersey</factoryItem> that I had received <num type="wage" amount=".05">5 cents</num>for finishing was offered to
        me at <num type="cost" amount="2.00">$2</num>. I declined.</nellVoice> <workingConditions category="negative">By way of interest, one hundred dozen garments are turned out of the
        factory every day in the year. As near as I could learn the salaries average $4 a week, but
        plenty of grown women are not allowed to earn over 28 cents a day. Work begins at 7:30 a. m.
        and 12:30 p. m. Anyone five minutes late working on time is fined an hour’s pay, and for the
        loss of an hour the pay of half a day is knocked off. Piece-workers who are late are kept
        idle form one to three hours. A girl who loses her ticket forfeits pay for the entire work,
        not withstanding the entry is on the books of the firm.</workingConditions> <headLine>LIFE AMONG THE SLAVE GIRLS
            OF <placeName type="city">CHICAGO</placeName></headLine>
        <headLine><ref to="theTimes">THE TIMES</ref></headLine> Will print tomorrow the second bath of facts concerning the
        workings of some of the factories of <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName> where girls and women are employed. <ref to="newspaperSeries">These
        articles are written by a young lady who passed through the common experiences of those
        unfortuantes of her own sex who are compelled to undergo the hardships and tortures of
        factory life in this city. She tells plainly what she saw ad what she heard; gives names and
        places whenever necessary, and backs up her statements with unquestionable proofs. These are
        revelations as unexpected as they are unpleasant.</ref> It was necessary that <ref to="theTimes">The Times</ref> should
        make them <desc of="upperClass">in order that the unthinking wealthy, well-to-do, and comfortable citizens of
        Chicago should have their eyes opened</desc>. If the condition of the working women and girls of
        this city is improved, even in a slight degree, by these exposures <ref to="theTimes">The Times</ref> will be fully
        repaid. Read <ref to="theTimes">The Times</ref> every day this week. <num type="cost" amount=".02">Two cents</num> per copy. Delivered by carrier, <num type="cost" amount=".12">12
            cents</num> per week for daily and <num type="cost" amount=".15">15 cents</num> per week for daily and Sunday. Order it by postal
        card, letter, or telephone 1362. </articleBody>
   </div>
</root>
