<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="Parker_simpleSampleRelaxNG.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <subjectLine>to <persName>Percy Bysshe Shelley</persName>, <address>Ravenna</address>, <date
            when="1821-04-26">April 26, 1821</date></subjectLine>

    <bodyParagraph>The <persName who="Allegra">child</persName> continues doing well, and the
        accounts are regular and favorable. It is gratifying to me that <persName
            who="Percy Bysshe Shelley">you</persName> and <persName>Mrs Shelley</persName> do not
        disapprove of the step which I have taken, which is merely temporary. I am very sorry to
        hear what you say of <litRef type="author">Keats</litRef> - is it actually true? I did not think
        criticism had been so killing. Though I differ from you essentially in your estimate of his
        performances, I so much abhor all unnecessary pain, that I would rather he had been seated
        on the highest peak of <placeName>Parnassus</placeName> than have perished in such a manner.
        Poor fellow! though with such inordinate self-love he would probably have not been very
        happy. I read the review of <litRef type="title">"Endymion"</litRef> in the <litRef
            type="title">Quarterly</litRef>. It was severe, - but surely not so severe as many
        reviews in that and other journals upon others. I recollect the effect on me of the
        <litRef type="title">Edinburgh</litRef> on my first poem; it was rage, and resistance, and redress - but not despondency
        nor despair. I grant that those are not amiable feelings; but, in this world of bustle and
        broil, and especially in the career of writing, a man should calculate upon his powers of
        resistance before he goes into the arena. <litRef type="quote">"Expect not life from pain nor danger free, Nor
        deem the doom of man reversed for thee."</litRef> You know my opinion of that second-hand school of
        poetry. You also know my high opinion of your own poetry, - because it is of no school. I
        read <litRef type="title">Cenci</litRef> - but, besides that I think the subject essentially undramatic, I am not an
        admirer of our old dramatists, as models. I deny that the English have hitherto had a drama
        at all. Your <litRef type="title">Cenci</litRef>, however, was a work of power, and poetry. As to my drama, pray revenge
        yourself upon it, by being as free as I have been with yours. I have not yet got your
        <litRef type="title">Prometheus</litRef>, which I long to see. I have heard nothing of mine, and do not know if it is yet
        published. I have published a pamphlet on the <litRef type="author">Pope</litRef> controversy, which you will not like. Had
        I known that <litRef type="author">Keats</litRef> was dead - or that he was alive and so sensitive - I should have omitted
        some remarks upon his poetry, to which I was provoked by his attack upon <litRef type="author">Pope</litRef>, and my
        disapprobation of his own style of writing. You want me to undertake a great Poem - I have
        not the inclination nor the power. As I grow older, the indifference - not to life, for we
        love it by instinct - but to the stimuli of life, increases. Besides, this late failure of
        the Italians has latterly disappointed me for many reasons, - some public, some personal. My
        respects to <persName>Mrs S.</persName></bodyParagraph>
    <closingLine>Yours ever. <persName>BYRON</persName>
    </closingLine>
    <postScript>P.S. Could not you and I contrive to meet this summer? Could not you take a run here
        alone?</postScript>

    <!--rjp: the following note resides at the bottom of the website page where this text was ripped from (The child Byron refers to was Allegra, his daughter with Shelley's sister-in-law Claire Clairmont.)-->
</root>
