<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <!--ebb: Need to rewrite XSLT to calculate dates from start to end of term. Non XSLT solution: To begin for a new year, autogenerate a list of dates and days of week in Excel (start with manually entering the first week's dates, and add +7 to each; format as ISO dates. 
            Paste in template xml file and autotag day and week divs. 
            Then manually correct with holidays and Fall Break, etc.-->
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Syllabus: or How to Make an Acceptable Offering for His Noodliness the Flying, Digitally Stupendous Spaghetti Monster</title>
            <author>Elisa E. Beshero-Bondar</author>
            <!--I'm adding a comment!!!-->
            <author>Gregory H. Bondar</author>
            <sponsor>The University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date from="2015-08" to="2015-12">Fall
                  2015</date>. P5.</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2014</date>
            <availability>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike
                  4.0 International License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>

            
            <p>Fall 3035 is the seven hundred and fiftieth time a version of this course has been taught, and this is the
>>>>>>> origin/master
               second XML edition of the syllabus. The first edition of this course syllabus was in
               Fall 2013, in HTML only at <ptr target="http://www.pitt.edu/~ebb8/DHDS/"/>.</p>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital.</p>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="courseID" style="outer">
            <head>Coding and Digital Archives</head>
            <p>Humanities 1030 / Social Sciences 1031</p>
            <div type="logo">
               <head>
                  <graphic url="blue-eye-icon-transMed.png" mimeType="image/png"/>
                  <desc>Pitt-Greensburg Digital Studies Logo: I Code!</desc>
               </head>
            </div>

            <div type="meetTimes">
               <p>
                  <hi rend="em">Autumn 2015:</hi> Classes meet M W F 10:30 - 11:20 AM, 116 Cassell
                  Hall</p>
            </div>
            <div type="CRN">
               <p>Course Enrollment and Electives Info: </p>
               <list>
                  <item>Hum 1030: (Digital Humanities) course registration number:
                        <idno>21120</idno>
                  </item>
                  <item>Socsci 1031: (Digital Studies) course registration number:
                        <idno>24531</idno>
                  </item>
                  <item>Satisfies a core course requirement for <ref target="http://greensburg.pitt.edu/academics/info/digital-studies">Pitt-Greensburg's Digital Studies Certificate</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fulfills HM, NS, and SS General Electives at Pitt-Greensburg</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="faculty">
               <head>Instructors</head>
               <p>co-taught by: <ref target="http://www.pitt.edu/~ebb8/">Prof. Elisa
                     Beshero-Bondar</ref>; email: ebb8 at pitt.edu and <ref target="http://www.personal.psu.edu/ghb1/">Prof. Gregory Bondar</ref>; email:
                  ghb2 at pitt.edu</p>
               <p>Elisa's Office Hours in <hi rend="em">FOB 204</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <!--ebb: check this!-->
                  <item>Wed. 11:30 AM -12:30 PM</item>
                  <item>Thurs. 3-6 PM</item>
                  <item>and by appointment</item>
               </list>
               <p>Greg's Office Hours in <hi rend="em">FOB 104</hi>
               </p>
               <!--ebb: Check with Greg about this! -->
               <list>
                  <item>Mon. 11:30 AM - 12:30 PM</item>
                  <item>Mon., Wed., and Fri. 2 - 3 PM</item>
                  <item>and by appointment</item>
               </list>

            </div>
            <div type="online">
               <head>Administrative:</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="http://newtfire.org/dh/CDA.html">Course Website:
                        http://newtfire.org/dh/CDA.html</ref> Home of our syllabus and schedule.</item>
                  <!--ebb: UPDATE with Discussion Board Info-->
                  <item>Course Discussion Board: To Be
                     Announced<!--<ref target="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!categories/pitt-greensburg-dhds"> (Google Group): https://groups.google.com/forum/#!categories/pitt-greensburg-dhds</ref>--></item>


                  <item>
                     <ref target="https://courseweb.pitt.edu">Courseweb:
                        https://courseweb.pitt.edu</ref> To submit homework assignments and read
                     private course announcements</item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="http://dh.obdurodon.org/file-naming_conventions.html">File-Naming Conventions for Courseweb Homework Submissions</ref>
                     <note> (courtesy of Obdurodon)</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="https://pitt.box.com">Pitt's Box Environment:
                        https://pitt.box.com</ref> for collaboration on projects</item>
                  <item>Server Access Instructions for Web Project Development: To Be Announced
                     <!--<ref target="SremoteSandboxInstruct.pdf">Pitt-Greensburg's Digital Sandbox Access Instructions</ref>: for Web Project Development--></item>

               </list>

            </div>
            <div type="projects">
               <head>Course Projects</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="projectGuide.html">Guidelines for Projects Developed in This
                        Course</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="studentProjects.html">Student Course Projects</ref>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="guides">
               <head>
                  <ref target="index.html">Explanatory Guides</ref>
               </head>
               <list>

                  <item>
                     <ref target="explainXML.html">Introduction to XML</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="explainRNG.html">Guide to Schema Writing with Relax
                     NG</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="explainHTML.html">Introduction to XHTML (and HTML)</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="explainCSS.html">Introduction to Cascading Stylesheets
                        (CSS)</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="explainXPath.html">Follow the XPath!</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="explainRegex.html">Regular Expression Matching
                     (Regex)</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="explainXSLT.html">Introduction to XSLT</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>SVG Tutorials, Editors, and Ideas: <list>
                        <item>
                           <ref target="http://tutorials.jenkov.com/svg/index.html">Jakob
                              Jenkov's SVG Tutorial</ref>: very thorough and handy reference</item>

                        <item>
                           <ref target="http://www.w3schools.com/svg/svg_intro.asp">w3 schools
                              SVG tutorial</ref>: a quick introduction, but not so thorough at the
                           Jenkov tutorial</item>
                        <item>
                           <ref target="http://www.math.wsu.edu/kcooper/M300/svgcheat.php">SVG
                              Cheat Sheet</ref>
                        </item>
                        <item>Obdurodon: <ref target="http://dh.obdurodon.org/svg-embedding.xhtml">How to Embed SVG in an XHTML Page</ref>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <ref target="http://www.carto.net/svg/samples/xslt/">carto:net: Using
                              XSLT to create SVG Content</ref>: We do all this in oXygen, but this
                           shows an alternative command-line processing of XSLT. </item>
                        <item>
                           <ref target="http://www.mathsisfun.com/geometry/unit-circle.html">Geometry of a Circle</ref> (for help if you want to plot points or
                           wedges on a circle). </item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <item>Editors: (good for some freeform work): <ref target="http://svg-edit.googlecode.com/svn/branches/2.5.1/editor/svg-editor.html">Google Code Online SVG Editor</ref>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <ref target="http://inkscape.org/en/">Inkscape</ref>: free SVG
                           software</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <item>Ideas: <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diagram">Wikipedia's
                              page on diagrams</ref>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chart">Wikipedia on
                              charts</ref>
                        </item>

                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="explainXQuery.html">XQuery and the eXist XML
                     Database</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>Javascript Resources: <list>
                        <item>
                           <ref target="http://dh.obdurodon.org/javascript.html">Introduction to
                              Javascript</ref>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <ref target="http://dh.obdurodon.org/javascript/classListToggle.xhtml">Javascript Toggling with classList and switch</ref>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="http://ebeshero.github.io/thalaba/cytosc.html">Introduction to
                        Network Analysis and Cytoscape for XML Coders</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mapping</item>


               </list>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="description" style="main">
            <head>Coding and Digital Archives: Course Description</head>
            <p>This course is all about doing interesting things with texts using computers and
               digital technology. We think of "texts" as the transmittable, sharable forms of human
               creativity made out of language, and we interface with a particular text in multiple
               ways through print and electronic "documents." When we refer to a "document," we mean
               a specific instance of a text, and much of our work will be in experimenting with the
               structures of texts in digital document formats, accessing them through scripts we
               write in computer code—scripts that in themselves a form of text, readable both by
               humans and machines. </p>
            <p> Your professors are scholars and teachers of humanities, not computer programmers, and we teach this course from our backgrounds (in literature and anthropology,
               respectively). We teach this course to share coding methods that are highly useful to
               us in our fields, with an emphasis on working with texts as artifacts of human
               culture shaped primarily with words and letters—the forms of "written" language
               transferable to many media (including image and sound) that we can study with
               computer modelling tools that we design for ourselves based on the questions we ask.
               We work with computers in this course as precision instruments that help us to read
               and process great quantities of information, and that lead us to make significant
               connections, ask new kinds of questions, and build models and interfaces to change
               our reading and thinking experience as people curious about human history, culture,
               and creativity. </p>
            <p>The course is designed to be interdisciplinary and practical, with an emphasis on
               learning through "hands-on" experience. Our emphasis in this course is primarily
               analytical: to apply computer technologies to represent and investigate cultural
               materials. As we design projects together, you will gain practical experience in
               editing and you will certainly fine-tune your precision in writing and thinking. We
               will be working primarily with eXtensible Markup Language (XML) because it is a
               powerful tool for modelling texts that we can adapt creatively to our interests and
               questions. XML represents a standard in adaptability and human-readability in digital
               code, and it works together with related technologies with which you will gain
               working experience: You'll learn how to write XPath expressions: a formal language
               for searching and extracting information from XML code which serves as the basis for
               transforming XML into many publishable forms, using XSLT and XQuery. You'll learn to
               write XSLT: a programming "stylesheet" transforming language designed to convert XML
               to publishable formats, as well as XQuery, a query (or search) language for
               extracting information from XML files bundled collectively. You will learn how to
               design your own systematic coding methods to work on projects, and how to write your
               own rules in schema languages (like Schematron and Relax-NG) to keep your projects
               organized and prevent errors. You'll gain experience with an international XML
               language called TEI (after the Text Encoding Initiative) which serves as the
               international standard for coding digital archives of cultural materials. Since one
               of the best and most widely accessible ways to publish XML is on the worldwide web,
               you'll gain working experience with HTML code (a markup language that is a kind of
               XML) and styling HTML with Cascading Stylesheets (CSS). We will do all of this with
               an eye to your understanding how coding works—and no longer relying without question
               on expensive commercial software as the "only" available solution, because such
               software is usually not designed with our research questions in mind. </p>
            <p>We think you'll gain enough experience at least to become a little dangerous, and at
               the very least more independent as investigators and makers who wield computers as
               fit instruments for your own tasks. Your success will require patience, dedication,
               and regular communication and interaction with us, working through assignments on a
               daily basis. Your success will NOT require perfection, but rather your regular
               efforts throughout the course, your documenting of problems when your coding doesn't
               yield the results you want. Homework exercises are a back-and-forth, intensive
               dialogue between you and your instructors, and we plan to spend a great deal of time
               with you individually over these as we work together. Our guiding principle in
               developing assignments and working with you is that the best way for you to learn and
               succeed is through regular practice as you hone your skills. Our goal is not to make
               you expert programmers (as we are far from that ourselves)! Rather, we want you to
               learn how to manipulate coding technologies for your own purposes, how to track down
               answers to questions, how to think your way algorithmically through problems and find
               good solutions.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="objectives" style="main">
            <head>Learning Objectives:</head>
            <list>
               <item>Work with Texts as Artifacts—As Physical and Virtual Objects: <list>

                     <item>Generate "digital surrogates": digitally represent facsimiles of rare
                        manuscripts and other kinds of documents, and make their content digitally
                        searchable.</item>
                     <item>Reflect and write on the issues and problems with digital representation,
                        as well as the capacity of the digital medium to enhance or add dimensions
                        to a physical text.</item>

                     <item>Learn and practice coding in eXtensible Markup Language (XML) and related
                        coding technologies: to "mark up," process, and extract information about
                        the structure, physical condition, and cultural contexts of textual
                        artifacts.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Gain Experience with Information Retrieval, "Distant Reading," and Autotagging
                  Techniques: <list>
                     <item>Write code to apply searching and data extraction methods through
                        multiple kinds of pattern-matching algorithms, including forms of regular
                        expression matching. Take conventional boolean searches and library database
                        searches to new levels.</item>
                     <item>Apply "mining" and "drilling" methods associated with "distant reading"
                        to apply computers to read and design more and differently than we could do
                        "manually" or with unassisted eyes and brains. </item>
                     <item>Learn how to "autotag" enormous texts or collections of texts, for
                        practical results: to code the structure of enormous texts from a distance,
                        in order to navigate them and make them accessible through distant
                        reading.</item>
                     <item>Reflect on and test the strong and weak points of "distant reading" and
                        processing methods: (What do we learn, and what is at stake in current
                        applications of digital "distant reading"?)</item>

                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Gain Project Design and Editing Experience: <list>
                     <item>Gain digital editing experience with proposing, designing, and
                        contributing to one or more digital research projects, applying coding to
                        the preserving, sharing, and investigating of textual resources</item>
                     <item>Transform XML code into publishable web formats, to build or contribute
                        to a project website.</item>
                     <item>Design navigation elements, and build visual aids and models (such as
                        timelines and tree diagrams) from texts: to generate charts and images from
                        extracted data</item>
                     <item>Gain experience with plotting digital maps and charts, working with
                        historical maps, layered maps, and Google Earth</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Last but not least: Discover that you read and write with "new eyes," with
                  greater precision and agility, thanks to your adventures in working with digital
                  texts!</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="courseMtls" style="main">
            <head>Required Course Materials: Software and Box Access You'll Need:</head>
            <p>Download and install the following software on your own personal computer(s). These
               are available in our campus computing labs, too.</p>
            <list type="numbered">
               <item>
                  <hi rend="em">All students:</hi>
                  <ref target="http://www.oxygenxml.com/">&lt;oXygen/&gt;</ref>. The University of
                  Pittsburgh has purchased a site license for this software, which is installed in
                  the Pitt computer labs on multiple campuses, and it's in use in courses here at
                  Greensburg and at Oakland. The license also permits students enrolled in the
                  course to install the software on their home computers (for course-related use
                  only). When installing this on your own computers, <hi rend="em">you will need the
                     license key</hi>, which we have posted on our course Announcements section of
                     <ref target="https://courseweb.pitt.edu">Courseweb</ref>.</item>
               <item>All students require a good means of secure file transfer (SFTP) for homework
                  assignments and projects (also available in the campus computer labs). There are
                  several good options available. We recommend you download and install on your own
                  computers one (or more) of the following, depending on your platform: (Feel free
                  to experiment with these and others!) <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi rend="em">Windows users:</hi> one of the following—the functionality
                        is similar: <list>
                           <item>
                              <ref target="http://www.wm.edu/offices/it/services/software/licensedsoftware/webeditingsftp/sshsecureshell/index.php">SSH Secure Shell Client</ref>
                              <note> (this one is the most ad-free experience)</note>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <ref target="http://winscp.net/eng/download.php">WinSCP</ref>
                              <note> (This is the one Greg and I "grew up" using over the
                                 years)</note>
                           </item>
                           <item> or <ref target="https://filezilla-project.org/download.php?show_all=1">FileZilla</ref>
                              <note> (a great tool, but be wary of accepting its bundled ad offers
                                 as you install!)</note>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi rend="em">Mac users:</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <ref target="http://fetchsoftworks.com/fetch/">Fetch</ref>
                              (students may obtain free licenses at <ref target="http://fetchsoftworks.com/fetch/free">http://fetchsoftworks.com/fetch/free</ref>)</item>
                           <item>or <ref target="https://filezilla-project.org/download.php?show_all=1">FileZilla</ref>
                              <note>(a great tool, but be wary of accepting its bundled ad offers as
                                 you install!)</note>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi rend="em">Linux users:</hi> You probably don't need to install
                        anything, but look at how your system handles secure file transfer (SFTP).
                           <note>(FileZilla or other clients designed for Linux
                           environments.)</note>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="optionalTexts" style="main">
            <head>Optional Texts (Helpful Reference Guides):</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <bibl>
                     <author>Michael Kay</author>, <title>XSLT 2.0 and XPath 2.0: Programmer's
                        Reference</title>, <edition>4th edition</edition>
                     <publisher>(Wiley Publishing</publisher>, <date>2008</date>) <idno>ISBN-13:
                        978-0-470-19274-0</idno>
                  </bibl>
                  <note> This is really THE authoritative word
                     on XSLT and XPath, written by a designer of the official W3C specifications of
                     XSLT 2.0 that we're using. We are learning from this book ourselves and consult
                     it frequently! We're not requiring that you buy it, but we recommend it to have
                     a powerful reference at your fingertips and for learning more on your own.
                     There's a kindle edition available but poorly designed for searching, so we
                     (actually) prefer the hardcover print edition. If you're going to purchase it,
                     be sure you pick up the current edition (not the earlier ones).</note>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <bibl>
                     <title>The Web Design Pocket Guide Boxed Set</title> (includes 3 books:
                     The HTML Pocket Guide, The JavaScript Pocket Guide, and The CSS Pocket Guide)
                        <author>Authors: Bruce Hyslop, Lenny Burdette, and Chris Casciano</author>
                     <publisher>(Pearson / Peachpit Pocket Guides</publisher>, <date>2010</date>).
                        <idno>ISBN-13: 978-0321743749</idno>
                  </bibl>
                  <note> You can probably locate
                     much of the content of these books online, on sites like <ref target="http://www.w3schools.com/">w3schools.com</ref> (which we use
                     ourselves), but we've discovered that sometimes it's handy to have print
                     reference guides around when working on computer projects!</note>
               </item>

            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="grading" style="main">
            <head>Grading:</head>
            <div type="homework">
               <head>Homework Exercises (35%):</head>
               <p>Regular homework exercises are key to the active learning process in this course.
                  Each day will involve some small assignment, building to the larger course
                  projects. Students must complete (on time) at least 90% of each homework component
                  (coding assignments, short response papers, blog postings and responses, in order
                  to pass the course. For students who complete the 90% requirement, the homework
                  taken all together, is worth 35% of your course grade.</p>
               <div type="coding">
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="em">Coding assignments:</hi> These are assignments you'll complete by
                     writing code to achieve a specified result by applying a coding method you are
                     learning. Often, there will be multiple ways of accomplishing the task. You
                     will receive lots of feedback from us, in the form of posted results and
                     individual commentary on your assignments as needed. If you don't achieve the
                     result you want, you may still receive full credit so long as you have made a
                     serious attempt to describe your process, what else you tried, what results you
                     expected vs. what results you got, and what you think went wrong. Documenting
                     problems is key to the learning process, and sometimes the documentation
                     process helps lead you to the solution and always helps your learning
                     process.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="papers">
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="em">Response papers:</hi> We'll assign short response papers (about 1
                     to 2 pages) to online readings or as evaluations of significant digital
                     humanities web projects and resources. Your response should do more than
                     summarize the article or site (which you could just do by skimming or reading
                     the first paragraph), but should demonstrate a thoughtful reflection on
                     specific ideas and issues. When evaluating a web resource, don't simply praise
                     or condemn it without going into details about why a key component is effective
                     or poorly designed. Good response papers demonstrate care and reflection, and
                     you may choose to respond to the overarching ideas of a piece, or to selected
                     details of specific interest. </p>
               </div>
               <div type="blogPost">
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="em">Project postings:</hi> These will begin on our discussion board
                     after you have formed teams to work on the course project. As you work on
                     course projects in teams, we expect that each team (not each individual
                     student) will post a project update, usually by Friday of a given week. These
                     postings should be brief status reports about your project work: what you've
                     accomplished in the preceding week, what problems you're facing, what you've
                     been learning, resources you've been discussing, and should conclude by
                     discussing what you plan to do the following week.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="blogResponse">
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="em">Project responses:</hi> Again, these begin after you have formed
                     project teams. Each student (not each team this time) must post one response to
                     a blog posting by some other team, usually due on a Monday (or the class period
                     following the team project posts). These responses can be brief but for credit
                     (and to be useful) they need to be thoughtful: something more than "good work!"
                     or "very interesting!" Respond to something specific in teh blog: make a
                     suggestion, offer a critique, ask or answer a question, discuss how something
                     in the blog post gave you an idea for your project, share a resource you've
                     found that may be helpful for the others.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="participation">
               <head>Participation: In Class and on the Discussion Board (15%):</head>
               <p> Coding and programming in real life is a social activity, and professionals in
                  the real world aren't "know-it-all" experts who work alone, but rather are tuned
                  into discussion boards and regularly ask and answer questions to stay sharp and to
                  learn from their community. In this class, we want you to work together and talk
                  to each other and your instructors as your community resource, so we have built
                  this into our course participation grade as a formal expectation. <hi rend="em">Beginning by week two, we'll expect each student to post at least once per
                     week on our online class discussion board</hi>, and we strongly encourage you
                  to do more than this minimum. Ask questions, make suggestions, share helpful
                  resources you've found. Help each other out by trying to answer questions (and
                  read the instructor posts too as we wade in to help). Your instructors will likely
                  be dominating the class time as we model concepts and methods, so the discussion
                  boards give you all a good space to form into a coding community to help each
                  other and reflect together. Also, if you have a question about an assignment, <hi rend="em">always think of the discussion board as your first resource</hi> to
                  check for helpful hints and to post your questions, because others may have the
                  same question and answers are best shared! Of course you may e-mail us, but we
                  really prefer you go the discussion board first, and doing so is, after all, worth
                  course credit as your participation grade.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="exams">
               <head>Quizzes and Tests (15%):</head>
               <p>As scheduled throughout the course there will be several (probably about six to
                  eight) short quizzes and tests that will take roughly half of the class period
                  time. These will ask you to demonstrate your knowledge of coding practices and
                  vocabulary learned in an immediately preceding portion of the course. We will drop
                  your lowest two scores on these exams. (No make-up exams are given: see course
                  policies below.) </p>
            </div>
            <div type="final-project">
               <head>Project (35%):</head>
               <p> Within the first three weeks of the course, we will familiarize you with some of
                  our ongoing projects and their associated research questions. These include the
                     <ref target="http://pacific.pitt.edu">Digital Archives and Pacific Cultures
                     Site</ref>, <ref target="http://mitford.pitt.edu">the Digital Mitford
                     Archive</ref>, and a site presenting <ref target="http://www.pitt.edu/~ebb8/EmilyDickinson16/1601.html">manuscript
                     variants in Emily Dickinson's Fascicle 16</ref>. We will also assign you to
                  propose a project based on a text or set of texts that interest you and suggest a
                  promising research question to explore with our coding methods, and we'll respond
                  to these to help you refine your ideas. We'll ask you all to read each other's
                  refined proposals, and the class as a whole (working with the instructors) will
                  select which of these we want to pursue through the term, and form groups to begin
                  work. Development of the project will involve doing a careful document analysis,
                  developing a coding plan and rules to follow, coding your text(s), and developing
                  programs to address your research question. It will also involve designing a
                  project site to represent your research questions, the texts and your processing
                  of them, as well as to share your coding scripts and to reflect on the results of
                  your investigation. We will post milestones you must meet for the projects
                  throughout the term. Project teams must meet 90% of the project milestone due
                  dates in order to receive a passing grade. It is expected that project teams meet
                  regularly (each week), check in with the instructors, and delegate tasks to each
                  other. Reporting on project progress is required as part of the regular homework
                  assignments for the course. Teams are encouraged to meet with us instructors
                  during (or outside) our scheduled office hours. In the last few weeks of the
                  course, almost all of your course work outside class will be devoted to project
                  development, applying the methods you've been learning across the semester.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="scale">
               <head>Grading Scale:</head>
               <p>Grades are posted on Courseweb, and follow this standard scale: A: 93-100%, A-:
                  90-92%, B+: 87-89%, B: 83-86%, B-: 80-82%, C+: 77-79%, C: 73-76%, C-: 70-72%, D+:
                  67-69%, D: 60-66%, F: 59% and below. In taking the course on a S / NC (pass-fail)
                  basis, students must earn a C to receive Satisfactory credit. We give G grades
                  (incomplete) at our discretion and only in conformity with the guidelines in the
                  Pitt-Greensburg Bulletin: <ref target="http://www.bulletins.pitt.edu/greensburg/upg-academicpolicies.htm#Anchor-Grading-9431">http://www.bulletins.pitt.edu/greensburg/upg-academicpolicies.htm#Anchor-Grading-9431</ref>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="policies" style="main">
            <head>Course Policies:</head>
            <p>Each day we are covering material that builds on earlier material and assignments, so
               your success depends upon regular attendance and completing each assignment on
               time.</p>
            <div type="daily">
               <head>Attendance:</head>
               <p> We strictly require your attendance, as it is not only a setback to yourself but
                  to the entire class and the success of our projects if students are repeatedly
                  absent. Students must attend at least 90% of our class meetings in order <hi rend="em">to pass</hi> the course. Late arrival—particularly a pattern of
                  repeated late arrivals—may be counted as absences at our discretion. Attendance
                  will be recorded for every class, and each student can earn percentage points
                  added towards their total course grade based on the following scale: Zero or one
                  absence: +3 pts; Two absences: +2 pts; Three or more: +0 pts. To earn credit, you
                  must be present in the classroom by the beginning of class, until class is
                  dismissed. For your own sanity, do not miss two consecutive classes. If you are
                  experiencing a genuine emergency or crisis, alert us and provide documentation.
                  (We do not want you to attend class if you have a fever or flu-like symptoms! If
                  you wish to be excused from two or more consecutive class meetings due to your own
                  documented illness, please contact one of the following: the Office of the Vice
                  President for Academic Affairs, Prof. Wes Jamison (724-836-9988 or jamison at
                  pitt.edu), our Campus Health Center (Nurse Patty or Pamela Reed, 724-836-9947 or
                  upgdoc at pitt.edu), or the Director of Counseling, Gayle Pamerleau (gaylep at
                  pitt.edu), who can then officially alert all of your professors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="deadlines">
               <head>Deadlines:</head>
               <p> Your daily homework for this course is time-sensitive! Coding assignments,
                  response papers, and other homework exercises must be uploaded to CourseWeb (or to
                  Box, or the Sandbox server as specified), by the date and time indicated by the
                  instructors. Homework assignments will be posted online to our class DHDS website
                  and linked from our schedule, so students who miss class are nevertheless expected
                  to consult the schedule and submit assignments on time. Because we post and share
                  answers to homework exercises after submission deadlines, we will not accept late
                  homework submissions. In order to pass the course, students must submit at least
                  90% of the regular homework assignments, and complete at least 90% of the work in
                  each component of the course.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="makeUp">
               <head>Exam Policy:</head>
               <p> Similarly, because we will be posting answers or sharing them in class, we do not
                  give make-up examinations. However, we will drop your lowest two exam scores for
                  the class, so that you may miss up to two exams without penalty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="courtesy">
               <head>Classroom Courtesy:</head>
               <p>Our class is fast paced, and requires that we all be making the best use we can of
                  our in-person class sessions. Arriving late and leaving early disrupts the
                  important collective mental activity of class. So does in-class texting and
                  checking your cell phone. While class is in progress, talking disruptively,
                  leaving the classroom, texting or using a cell phone or computer, reading a
                  newspaper, or other distracting behavior will be actively discouraged, and may
                  result in a deduction in your Participation grade. Please respect what we do in
                  the classroom: attend class regularly, and come prepared to contribute your
                  questions and ideas.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="email">
               <head>E-mail:</head>
               <p>Each student is issued a University email address (username@pitt.edu) upon
                  admission. This email address may be used by the University for official
                  communication with students. Students are expected to read email sent to this
                  account on a regular basis. Failure to read and react to University communications
                  in a timely manner does not absolve the student from knowing and complying with
                  the content of the communications. The University provides an email forwarding
                  service that allows students to read their email via other service providers
                  (e.g., Hotmail, AOL, Yahoo). Students who choose to forward their email from their
                  pitt.edu address to another address do so at their own risk. If email is lost as a
                  result of forwarding, it does not absolve the student from responding to official
                  communications sent to their University email address. To forward email sent to
                  your University account, go to http://accounts.pitt.edu, log into your account,
                  click on Edit Forwarding Addresses, and follow the instructions on the page. Be
                  sure to log out of your account when you have finished. (For the full Email
                  Communication Policy, go to <ref target="http://www.bc.pitt.edu/policies/policy/09/09-10-01.html">http://www.bc.pitt.edu/policies/policy/09/09-10-01.html</ref>.)</p>
            </div>


            <div type="integrity">
               <head>Academic Integrity</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="em">Source Citation and Plagiarism:</hi> One goal of our course is to
                  reflect on how best to cite sources in digital contexts. We will consider how and
                  why such citations differ from documenting printed texts. We will also consider
                  the ease and frequency with which digital texts and graphics are plagiarized on
                  the worldwide web, and discuss how the omission of source citations detracts from
                  the authority of a digital information resource. We expect you to practice mindful
                  source citation, and plagiarism on your part will have very serious
                  consequences.</p>
               <p>Plagiarism falsely represents another source’s words or ideas as your own, and, if
                  you commit plagiarism in this course, you will receive a final course grade of F
                  and be reported to the Vice President of Academic Affairs. Representing the voice
                  of another individual as your own voice constitutes plagiarism, however generous
                  that person may be in “helping” you with an assignment. Turning in an assignment
                  generated collectively under the name of a single individual is considered
                  plagiarism. <hi rend="em">When instructed to collaborate on a project, project
                     collaborators share collective authorship and should identify themselves
                     directly as a team.</hi> To avoid plagiarism, cite your sources whenever you
                  quote, paraphrase, or summarize material, or use digital images from any outside
                  source (including websites, articles, books, course readings, Courseweb postings,
                  or someone else’s notes). When using the “copy” and “paste” features as you read
                  and research, be sure that you are carefully marking that these passages are
                  unprocessed from their source, so that you know to process it later. Forgetting to
                  do so not only produces sloppy work but (whether you intended it or not) results
                  in a false representation. As long as you make a good faith and clear effort to
                  cite your sources, you will not be faulted for plagiarism, but your work will be
                  penalized if citations are inaccurate, unclear, or lack important information.
                  Cheating on exams or exercises will also receive a final course grade of F and
                  will be reported to the Vice President of Academic Affairs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="disability">
               <head>Disability Services:</head>
               <p>If you have a disability for which you are or may be requesting an accommodation,
                  you are encouraged to contact both your instructor and the Director of the
                  Learning Resources Center, Dr. Lou Ann Sears, Room 240 Millstein Library Building
                  (724) 836-7098 (voice) or los3 at pitt.edu as early as possible in the term.
                  Learning Resources Center will verify your disability and determine reasonable
                  accommodations for this course.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="resources">
            <head>Resources</head>
            <p>We gratefully acknowledge <ref target="http://dh.obdurodon.org/">David Birnbaum's
                  Digital Humanities course</ref> as our starting point and resource for much of our
               development. Other useful resources include:</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <ref target="https://exam.obdurodon.org/">eXam Center</ref>: a learning
                  resource for quizzing yourself on coding that we're learning in class. <note>(We
                     need to arrange for you to have individual accounts here to sign in and take
                     the quizzes.)</note>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="http://www.mulberrytech.com/papers/schematron-Philly.pdf">Schematron: an intro guide</ref>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/">The Programming
                     Historian (full collection of tutorials)</ref>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="http://programminghistorian.org/lessons/topic-modeling-and-mallet">Getting Started with Topic Modelling and MALLET</ref>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="http://www.naturalearthdata.com/">Natural Earth (mapping
                     resource)</ref>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="extProjects">
            <head>Projects and Sites That Inspire Us</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <ref target="http://obdurodon.org">Obdurodon</ref>: where we learned what we
                  can teach, and where we're still learning...</item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="http://mapoflondon.uvic.ca/index.htm">Map of Early Modern
                     London</ref>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="http://lordbyron.cath.lib.vt.edu/index.php?choose=About">Lord
                     Byron and His Times</ref>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="http://shelleygodwinarchive.org/">The Shelley-Godwin
                  Archive</ref>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="http://jetson.unl.edu:8080/cocoon/tokenx/index.html?file=../xml/base.xml">TokenX: a text visualization, analysis, and play tool</ref>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="http://homes.cs.washington.edu/~jheer//files/zoo/">A Tour Through
                     the Visualization Zoo</ref> (Lots of fascinating approaches to visualizing
                  information in dynamic graphs and maps)</item>
               <item>
                  <ref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Xe1TZaElTAs">Clay Shirky on Love,
                     Internet Style</ref> (9 minutes of Youtube inspiration: on what lasts, and why
                  community matters in our digital worlds.)</item>

            </list>
         </div>


         <div type="schedule">
            <head>Coding and Digital Archives: Schedule</head>
            <div type="week" n="1">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-08-31">M 08-31</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-09-02">W 09-02</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-09-04">F 09-04</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week" n="2">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-09-07">M 09-07</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Labor Day Holiday: No classes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-09-09">W 09-09</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-09-11">F 09-11 <note>drop-add period ends</note>
                     </date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week" n="3">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-09-14">M 09-14</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-09-16">W 09-16</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-09-18">F 09-18</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week" n="4">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-09-21">M 09-21</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-09-23">W 09-23</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-09-25">F 09-25</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week" n="5">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-09-28">M 09-28</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-09-30">W 09-30</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-02">F 10-02</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week" n="6">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-05">M 10-05</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-07">W 10-07</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-09">F 10-09</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week" n="7">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-12">M 10-12</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-14">W 10-14</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-16">F 10-16</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week" n="8">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-19">M 10-19</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fall Break: Monday classes meet on Tuesday this week.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-20">T 10-20</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-21">W 10-21</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-23">F 10-23</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week" n="9">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-26">M 10-26</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-28">W 10-28</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-10-30">F 10-30</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week" n="10">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-11-02">M 11-02</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-11-04">W 11-04</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-11-06">F 11-06</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week" n="11">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-11-09">M 11-09</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-11-11">W 11-11</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-11-13">F 11-13</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week" n="12">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-11-16">M 11-16</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-11-18">W 11-18</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-11-20">F 11-20</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week" n="13">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-11-23">M 11-23</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-11-25">W 11-25 to F 11-27</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thanksgiving Recess: No Classes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
   
         
     
            <div type="week" n="14">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-11-30">M 11-30</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-12-02">W 12-02</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-12-04">F 12-04</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week" n="15">
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-12-07">M 12-07</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-12-09">W 12-09</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="day">
                  <head>
                     <date when="2015-12-11">F 12-11 (Last Day of Classes)</date>
                  </head>
                  <div type="inclass">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="assign">
                     <p>. . . .</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="week">
               <div type="day"><head><date>Thurs. 12/17 by 11:59 PM</date></head>
               <div type="assign">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Projects due.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div></div>

         </div>


      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
