<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<LordByron1811Letter> 
    <MentionedIndividuals>
        <Author>I="Lord Byron"></Author>
        <Religious_Figure>Christ="Jesus Christ", Nazarene="Jesus Christ"></Religious_Figure>
        <Deceased_Friend>Matthews="Charles Matthews"></Deceased_Friend>
        <Acquaintance>Scrope Davies, assumed to be associate or partner</Acquaintance>
    </MentionedIndividuals>
    <Ideologies>
        <Religious_Denomination>Paulician="Christian"></Religious_Denomination>
        <Philosophy>Spinozist="Adhering to teachings of Baruch Spinoza"></Philosophy>
        <Philosophy>Pyrrhonian="Adhering to skeptic belief system of Pyrrho></Philosophy>
        <Philosophy>Galileeism="A slang used by Byron to indicate people who adhere to Galilee's methods"></Philosophy>
        <Religion>Manichean="Adhering to teachings of the Iranian Prophet, Mani"></Religion>
        <Religion>Zoroastrianism="A follower of the Prophet Zoroaster and his teachings"></Religion>
        <Religious_Classification>Gentile="A Non-Jew"></Religious_Classification>
        <Religious_Classification>Mussulman="Muslim, a follower of Islam"></Religious_Classification>     
    </Ideologies>
    <Locations>
        <Asia>Judaea="The past name of Israel during the Roman Empire"></Asia>
        <Asia>Galilee="The northern region of Israel, divided into Lower and Upper Galilee"></Asia>
        <Africa>Timbuctoo="A misspelling of Timbuktu, a populous city in Mali"></Africa>
        <Oceania>Otaheite="The largest island in all of French Polynesia"></Oceania>
    </Locations>
    <Dates>
        <Date_of_letter>September_3_1811="Day of Letter being written"</Date_of_letter>
    </Dates>
    <Letter_Content>
    <Introduction>My dear Hodgson, I will have nothing to do with your immortality; we are
    miserable enough in this life, without the absurdity of speculating upon another. If men are to
    live, why die at all? and if they die, why disturb the sweet and sound sleep that ‘knows no
    waking’?</Introduction> 
    <Body_Paragraph_One>‘Post Mortem nihil est, ipasque Mors nihil… quaeris quo jaceas post obitum loco? Quo
    non Nata jacent.’ As to revealed religion, Christ came to save men; but a good Pagan will go to
    heaven, and a bad Nazarene to hell; ‘Argal’ (I argue like the gravedigger) why are not all men
    Christians? or why are any? If mankind may be saved who never heard or dreamt, at Timbuctoo,
    Otaheite, Terra Incognita, etc., of Galilee and its Prophet, Christianity is of no avail: if
    they cannot be saved without, why are not all orthodox? It is a little hard to send a man
    preaching to Judaea, and leave the rest of the world – Negers and what not – dark as their
    complexions, without a ray of light for so many years to lead them on high; and who will believe
    that God will damn men for not knowing what they were never taught? I hope I am sincere; I was
    so at least on a bed of sickness in a far-distant country, when I had neither friend, nor
    comforter, nor hope, to sustain me. I looked to death as a relief from pain, without a wish for
    an after-life, but a confidence that the God who punishes in this existence had left that last
    asylum for the weary.</Body_Paragraph_One> 
    <Body_Paragraph_Two>I am no Platonist, I am nothing at all; but I would sooner be a Paulician,
    Manichean, Spinozist, Gentile, Pyrrhonian, Zoroastrian, than one of the seventy-two villainous
    sects who are tearing each other to pieces for the love of the Lord and hatred of each other.
    Talk of Galileeism? Show me the effects – are you better, wiser, kinder by your precepts? I will
    bring you ten Mussulmans shall shame you in all goodwill towards men, prayer to God, and duty to
    their superiors. And is there a Talapoin, or a Bonze, who is not superior to a fox-hunting
    curate? But I will say no more on this endless theme; let me live, well if possible, and die
    without pain. The rest is with God, who assuredly, had He come or sent, would have made Himself
    manifest to nations, and intelligible to all. I shall rejoice to see you.</Body_Paragraph_Two> 
    <Conclusion>My present intention
    is to accept Scrope Davies’s invitation; and then, if you accept mine, we shall meet here and
    there. Did you know poor Matthews? I shall miss him much at Cambridge.</Conclusion> 
    </Letter_Content>
</LordByron1811Letter>
