<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="WarLettersSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<letter>
    <title>Trenches: "had a game of football"</title>
    
<abstract>This is one of many letters sent by staff of the Great Western Railway (GWR) Audit office at <placeName location="Paddington"></placeName> who had enlisted to fight in the 
First World War. (RAIL 253/516)</abstract>

<heading><persName firstName="Ernest" lastName="Bratchell"/>,France. Born: 28 July 1893, Joined GWR: 3 February 1908, Regiment: 1/3 (City of London) Battalion 
(Royal Fusiliers), Regiment number: 2176, Rank: Private, Died: 1969</heading>


<body>
    
    <p>Dear Burgie,</p>

<p>Was very glad indeed to get your letters although, your news in regard to <persName>Joe [Chamberlain]</persName> comes as a shock. It was the first
I had heard of him since he arrived in <placeName location="France"/> in spite of the fact his regiment being quite close. Am afraid the 9th and few days following were rotten days for a good
many battalions, our lot as much as any. We have been “in” since the 8th and have had a fairly trying time we were reinforced during this week, not
before time as we were down to our last two hundred. Can’t tell how sorry I am to hear about Joe as you say he was “one of the best”. I hope you 
chaps have not been annoyed at my not answering your very welcome letters. I don’t pride myself much on writing good yarns though and opportunities
are also hard to find. As you know I had a bit of a knock at <placeName location="Neuve Chappell"></placeName> but have quite got over that and am now in the <emotion morale="best of health and spirits"></emotion>.
I came across <persName>Len Phillips</persName> and <persName>Peter Hawes</persName> in different drafts of the <placeName location="London Scottish"></placeName> while down at
<placeName location="Rouen"></placeName> both of them have now had some experience on the job I expect. Thank <persName>Mr Drewe</persName> very much for making
inquiries, tell him I occasionally wish heartily to be on the old job again the quiet life
will do for me after this. No I did not get <persName>Dick’s</persName> magazine or letter expect it went astray while I was in hospital. Thank him very much for sending
them will you. Had a game of football about two weeks ago with R.G.A.* Battery, the pitch being a serious drawback. I think it was a cabbage patch.
Still we managed to get a good game in and most important of all, won. The weather here has on the whole been very good just lately only getting an
occasional day’s rain. Last night we had a sharp thunderstorm, a new experience it had at least the effect of shutting all the other disturbances 
of our rest up so we did not grouse. Much obliged for all the information re the other fellows. Am glad most of them are getting on so well. 
<persName>Peacock</persName> seems to have come out top dog. The job alone from other examples seems to be a paying one, leaving out the holiday in <placeName location="Scotland"></placeName>. Well 
must close my epistle. Please remember me to <persName>Dick</persName>, <persName>Mr Horsley</persName>, <persName>Ransley</persName> and <persName>Drewe</persName>, <persName>Fox</persName>.
Hoping both they, and yourself are, <emotion morale="like myself O.K."></emotion>
[Line censored].</p>

</body>

<closing>From yours faithfully,

<persName>E.W. Bratchell</persName></closing>

</letter>