<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to <persName ref="#Talfourd_Thos">T.N. Talfourd</persName>1821 November 09</title>
            <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author>
            <editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor>
            <sponsor>
               <orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName>
            </sponsor>
            <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor>
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
               <persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref="#ghb">[who?]</persName><!-- correct when proofed LMW -->
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: 27 May 2014. P5.</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <placeName >The John Rylands University Library</placeName>.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="#Rylands">The John Rylands University Library</repository>
                  <collection>Mitford-Talfourd Correspondence: Letters from Mary Russell Mitford to Thomas Noon Talfourd: vol. 665</collection>
                  <idno>JRL English MS 665 no. 5 Coles no. 18</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to T.N. Talfourd, <date when="1821-11-09">1821 November 9</date>. <!-- MRM dates this letter "Friday night" Coles dates it Nov. 9 based on MRM's diary. (Coles #18, p.111, note 1).  Nov. 9 was a Friday. LMW --> <!--DSCF6097, DSCF6098, DSCF6099 LMW --></head>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc>
                     <supportDesc>
                        <support> 
                           <p>Folio sheet of <material>paper</material> folded in half to form four
                              quarto pages, with correspondence on 1-3, then folded in thirds twice more.</p>
                        </support>
                        <condition>
                        <!--There is no image of page four, no address leaf, and Coles does not indicate that he has seen any page four or address leaf either.  LMW-->
                        </condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <sealDesc>
                     <seal> 
                        <p>
                        <!--There is no seal  LMW--></p>
                     </seal>
                  </sealDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <handNotes>
            <handNote xml:id="pencilRy"  medium="pencil">Someone cataloging the letters, apparently
               other than Mitford, numbered each on page 1. This letter numbered 13.</handNote>
         </handNotes>
  </profileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the
               end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s
               spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate
               searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both
               Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling,
               following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and
               ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place" ref="#ThreeMileCross">Three Mile Cross</name> 
                  <date when="1821-11-09">Friday night</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
            </opener>
            
            <p> Again &amp; again I thank you for your exquisite kindness.  I have just received <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/>Mr</del> your packet from <persName ref="#Newberry_J">Mr. Newberry</persName>, &amp; have read <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready's</persName> letter with the hopeful spirit that you desire &amp; with the truest gratitude to him &amp; to you.  His discovery of the sex of the unlucky writer made me laugh in spite of my vexation--I believe I could as soon pass myself for 6 feet <!-- Coles has "illegible" here LMW --> high as write two lines which should be taken for a man's composition.  Nevertheless I have great confidence in his exertions--the greatest--the most undoubting--&amp; I am heartily glad to be rid of those puny sources of interest, on which one can never feel any real or comfortable reliance.  With <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> &amp; <emph n="underline">You</emph> the <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Play</title> <pb n="2"/>  will have every possible chance that its own weakness will allow it--far more than it deserves.  I shall immediately begin the new Catastrophe.  Must there not be an entirely new fifth Act?  Some part of the scene with the <persName ref="#Doge_F">Doge</persName> may remain--but the opening of the scene with <persName ref="#Cosmo">Cosmo</persName> &amp; that with <persName ref="#Camilla"></persName>Camilla, must not these be new as well as the conclusion?  Or will a little altering &amp; modifying do?  He must <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="word"/><unclear/></del> have taken the poison before the beginning of the Act--And can we make him be sleeping so quietly afterwards? <del rend="squiggles"><gap quantity="1" unit="character"/><unclear/></del> And there must be through all his speeches a dark concealed consciousness of the coming death--I am afraid it must be quite new--but I will do my very best &amp; <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName> &amp; you can decide--you shall certainly have it by the middle of the week after next.  I wonder what <persName ref="#Byron">Lord Byron</persName>'s Catastrophe is!  We should steer clear of that at all events.  But we shall have plenty to chuse <choice><reg resp="lmw">choose</reg></choice> <pb n="3"/> out of that is one comfort.  I was not in the least disappointed, or disconcerted (except at that terrible "evidently a lady's") by <persName ref="#Macready_Wm">Mr. Macready</persName>'s opinion of the <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Play</title>--mine has always been much lower--really much lower--not a mere piece of affectation to be contradicted or to look modest but an unfeigned &amp; settled impression--I was therefore not in the least surprised or startled at that--but astonished &amp; delighted beyond measure at the zeal &amp; energy with which he takes up the cause--this of course proceeds entirely from his friendship for you--&amp; the kind interest which you have the goodness to take in my poor <title ref="#Foscari_MRMplay">Foscari</title>--Oh you have no notion with what a delightful feeling of assurance I rely, not as you bid me on him only, but on him &amp; you.--If we reduce the <persName ref="#Doge_F">Doge</persName>'s part so much I suppose we must retain the old title--But that will be time enough to consider. by &amp; bye.--Once more a thousand thanks &amp; regards &amp; good wishes from all</p>
            <closer>
               <lb/> Ever most gratefully yours<signed><persName ref="#MRM">MRMitford.</persName></signed><lb/>
            </closer>
               
             <postscript> 
                <p>Pray excuse all my blots &amp; blunders--I had better not have written. but I could not help it--</p>
            </postscript>   
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
            
            
           

 
   
