<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<?xml-model href="http://ebeshero.github.io/MRMValidate.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William Elford</persName>, <date when="1820-09-09">1820 September 9</date></title>
            <author ref="#MRM">Mary Russell Mitford</author>
            <editor ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</editor>
            <sponsor><orgName>Mary Russell Mitford Society: Digital Mitford Project</orgName></sponsor>
              <sponsor>University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg</sponsor> 
            <principal>Elisa Beshero-Bondar</principal>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcription and coding by</resp>
                  <persName ref="#efp">Elaine Frantz Parsons</persName>
                  <persName ref="#lmw">Lisa M. Wilson</persName>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Proofing and corrections by</resp>
               <persName ref="#ebb">Elisa Beshero-Bondar</persName><!--ebb: 1 February 2015: Proofread the transcription and coding, and processed site index entries from the two leaves we missed earlier. Also: adding information about the address leaf and postmarks.--><!-- Adding the two leaves we missed (new photos in box). 5 October 2014. LMW --><!--ebb: 1 July 2014: Proofread this against the manuscript images and updated the TEI header. Need to check at Reading CL if we missed photographing the last leaf.--> 
               
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>First digital edition in TEI, date: <date when="2014-07-01">1 July 2014</date>. P5.</edition>
            <respStmt><resp>Edition made with help from photos taken by</resp><orgName>Digital Mitford editors</orgName></respStmt>
            <respStmt><orgName>Digital Mitford</orgName><resp> photo files: <idno>DSCF8027.JPG, DSCF8028.JPG, DSCF8029.JPG, DSCF8030.JPG, DSCF8031.JPG, DSCF8032.JPG<!--ebb: These are the old image files, missing the last two leaves of the letter. 9Sept1820SirWilliamElford1.jpg, 9Sept1820SirWilliamElford2.jpg, 9Sept1820SirWilliamElford3.jpg, 9Sept1820SirWilliamElford4.jpg,--></idno></resp></respStmt> 
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</authority>
            <pubPlace>Greensburg, PA, USA</pubPlace>
            <date>2013</date>
            <availability>
               <p>Reproduced by courtesy of the <orgName ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</orgName>.</p>
               <licence>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported
                  License</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Digital Mitford Letters: The Mary Russell Mitford Archive</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         
         
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository ref="#ReadingCL">Reading Central Library</repository>
                  <collection>The letters of Mary Russell Mitford, vol. 4, 1819-1823</collection>
                  <idno>qB/TU/MIT Vol. 4 ff.441 Horizon No.: 1361550</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
 <head>Letter from Mary Russell Mitford to Sir William Elford, <date when="1820-09-09">1820 September 9</date>.</head>
               <physDesc>
               <objectDesc>
                  <supportDesc>
                  <support>One and one-half sheets of folio <material>paper</material>, six surfaces photographed. The letter was folded in thirds twice, and bears an address leaf with a black, circular mileage stamp, mostly illegible: <stamp><gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" quantity="1"/><unclear><supplied>R</supplied></unclear>EADING<lb/><gap reason="illegible"/></stamp></support>
                     
                     <condition>Half sheet (pages five and six) torn on right edge where wax seal was removed.</condition>
                     
               </supportDesc>
               </objectDesc>
                  <sealDesc><p>A red wax seal with the imprint <q>Mary</q>.</p></sealDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
        <handNotes>
           <handNote corresp="#rc" medium="red_crayon"> Red crayon or thick red pencil. Probably a different hand from Mitford's that marks many of her letters, sometimes drawing diagonal lines across pages, and sometimes writing words overtop and perpendicularly across Mitford's writing. On this letter, a red line is drawn from the top center diagonally slightly left to the bottom of the first page, and then is drawn in the usual way from top left to bottom right of each of the other leaves.</handNote>
           <handNote corresp="#pencil" medium="pencil"> Someone, apparently other than Mitford, perhaps cataloging letters and describing them, who left grey pencil marks and numbered her letters now in the Reading Central Library's collection. This letter is numbered "16" in the top left of the first leaf, underneath the opening line, "To Sir W. Elford."
           </handNote>
        </handNotes>
     </profileDesc>
     <encodingDesc>
           <editorialDecl>
              <p>Mitford’s spelling and punctuation are retained, except where a word is split at the end of a line and the beginning of the next in the manuscript. Where Mitford’s spelling and hyphenation of words deviates from the standard, in order to facilitate searching we are using the TEI elements “choice," “sic," and “reg" to encode both Mitford’s spelling and the regular international standard of Oxford English spelling, following the first listed spelling in the Oxford English Dictionary. The long s and ligatured forms are not encoded.</p>
           </editorialDecl>
     </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener> 
               <salute>To <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir W. Elford</persName></salute> 
               <add hand="#pencil">16</add> 
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place">Three Mile Cross</name>
                  <date when="1820-09-09">September 9<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> 1820</date>.
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>You will think <rs type="person" ref="#MRM">your poor little Friend</rs> very naughty indeed, my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName> if she do not sometimes write you two letters, so having made no vow by <placeName ref="#Styx">Styx</placeName> this time, she will scribble.<note resp="#ebb #lmw">In ancient Greek history and mythology, gods or mortals who make oaths by <placeName ref="#Styx">the River Styx</placeName> are understood to be strongly bound not to break them. The penalty for breaking an oath was to drink the poisonous water of this mythical river, which would stupefy the oath-breaker for an entire year.</note> Having nothing to say <metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/><add place="above">my dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName></add> is such an old story between us that there <del rend="squiggles">are</del><add place="above">is</add> no need of apologies on that score. I really think we go on quite as well without a subject as with one--the cobweb spins out to a good size--rather flimsy to be sure, &amp; not very durable--but there it is looking very happy &amp; comfortable these bright autumn mornings-- &amp; the poor little round spider snugs herself up in her hole and seems proud of her handywork <add>&amp; as soon as one is finished away begins another</add>.--So she shall spin on. Moreover, it behooves me to pay my court very spiderously, or I shall have my nose quite put <metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/><del rend="strikethrough">of</del><add place="above">out of</add> joint by that formidable rival <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Lady Madelina</persName>. I did wait on her as I told you I should, &amp; think with you that she is a most delightful woman. I did not expect to find her still so very handsome--but the best parts of beauty, grace intelligence &amp; and <choice><sic>goodhumour</sic><reg>good humour</reg></choice> are those which last the longest, &amp; and that pretty Scotch voice is enchanting. We talked a great deal of you--&amp; of <placeName ref="#Devonshire_county">Devonshire</placeName>--which she admires with her whole heart--&amp; she says things of you--It is very well that <persName ref="#Palmer_CF">Mr. Palmer</persName> was out of hearing--there is no love lost beween you <unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">I assure</supplied></unclear> you. In short I was quite charmed with every thing about her but her <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName> madness which burst forth suddenly on the appearance of <title ref="#Times_news">the Times</title> &amp; sent me off in a hurry. Had she this frenzy-fever in <placeName ref="#Devonshire">Devonshire</placeName> or has she caught it from <rs type="person" ref="#Palmer_CF">her husband</rs>? <orgName ref="#Palmerite">He &amp; his brother members &amp; his precious constituents</orgName> are alike insane upon this subject. Indeed to do <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> justice it never is behindhand in any<pb n="2"/> folly stirring. They had a meeting to address the <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName>--&amp; voted said address--&amp; sent up their worthy members to present it--&amp; up they went in all their paraphernalia--&amp; the gracious <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName> never spoke to them! Is not this famous? Never said a word, shoved the answer unread into their hands, held her tongue &amp; marched off. <said who="#Monck_Mrs">"Served them just right--did not she <persName ref="#MRM">Mary</persName>?" </said> <choice><sic>Said</sic><reg>said</reg></choice> <persName ref="#Monck_Mrs">Mrs. Monck</persName> to me when she told me the story--<said who="#Monck_Mrs">"a couple of simpletons. I only wish the whole meeting had been there to have partaken of the compliment."</said>&#xa0;<persName ref="#Monck_Mrs">Mrs. Monck</persName> you see is sane. Did I ever talk to you of <orgName ref="#Monck_family">the Moncks</orgName>? <persName ref="#Monck_JB">He</persName> is a very extraordinary man--a great Grecian--&amp; more like an old philosopher than anything you ever saw--I defy anything or anybody to put him out of humour--he has not of course though a clever man, <del rend="squiggles">any thing</del> <add place="above">much</add> of <persName ref="#Fox_ChasJ">Charles Fox</persName>'s powers or eloquence, but he is more like him in point of character than any man that ever lived--full of kindheartedness &amp; of a tolerant humanity--more generally beloved by man woman &amp; child than any person I ever heard of--Dividing his whole time between literature &amp; usefulness &amp; family affection. <persName ref="#Monck_Mrs">His wife</persName> is a pretty lively chatty woman kind &amp; good humored--entirely without her <choice><sic>husband's</sic><reg>husband's</reg></choice> largeness &amp; liberality of mind--not even understanding the breadth &amp; depth of his character--but in whom good habits &amp; kindly prejudices produce nearly the same effect. She loves his <metamark place="below" function="insertion" rend="caret"/><add place="above">old</add> friends because they are old friends, &amp; is good to the poor because she has been used to <del rend="strikethrough" unit="word" quantity="1">it.</del><add place="above">be charitable.</add>--She has returned from a three years &amp; a half tour through <placeName ref="#France">France</placeName> <placeName ref="#Italy">Italy</placeName> <placeName ref="#Switzerland">Switzerland</placeName> &amp; <placeName ref="#Germany">Germany</placeName> without having brought back a single new feeling or left behind one old one. She is so entirely unchanged in mind &amp; person as to produce an effect more extraordinary &amp; surprising than could have <del rend ="squiggle" unit="word" quantity="2"><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw #ebb">been the</supplied></unclear></del> resulted from the greatest alteration. She took up her <placeName ref="#Coley_Berks">Coley</placeName> habits, as if she had only laid them aside <pb n="3"/> the night before with her clothes, &amp; the presence of a sweet little girl of three years old born in <placeName ref="#France">France</placeName> &amp; and not speaking a word of English seems necessary to convince one that the Mother has ever set her foot on the Continent. This identity of character has a great charm with me--I never liked <persName ref="#Monck_Mrs">Mrs. Monck</persName> half so well in my life as since she returned so perfectly the same as she went. Besides we agree like two drops of water. She hates her <choice><sic>husbands</sic><reg>husband's</reg></choice> parliamenting. So do I. She sickens at the name of <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen Caroline</persName>. So do I. She thinks <placeName ref="#Mortimer_Comm">Mortimer Common</placeName> the prettiest place in the world. So do I. She detests <placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> and its doings. So do I.--<placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> is at present <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName> mad. It reads &amp; talks &amp; dreams &amp; lies of nothing else--&amp; engrafts a clumsy and awkward licentiousness on its original vulgarity &amp; dullness. After all the crying evil of this frightful enquiry is its tendency to confound right &amp; wrong. Those who dislike the <persName ref="#GeoIV">King</persName>'s immorality think themselves bound by the duty of party to palliate the much grosser and more horrible conduct of the <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName>, &amp; we hear of <q>"little indiscretions"</q> &amp; <q>"too great condescensions"</q> &amp; such paltering with vice from the very lips of the stern mentors who thunder at the crimes of Kings &amp; the wickedness of Ministers. This must be wrong--there can only be one Virtue &amp; one Wickedness. Besides the <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName>'s <del rend="squiggles">conduct</del><add place="above">defence</add> throws a stain &amp; a slur upon womanhood--She seeks to cover her enormous crime with a cloak of innocence &amp; purity &amp; profanes the sacred &amp; holy name of matronly virtue by asserting her claim to it. Chastity is become a <choice><sic>byeword</sic><reg resp="#lmw">byword</reg></choice> &amp; a jest--She is to womanly purity, what a false prophet is to religion. She can not alter the eternal truth--but she can give mockers &amp; scoffers a pretence to doubt <choice><sic>it's</sic><reg>its</reg></choice> existence. Many years must pass away before the effect of this ceases &amp; modesty shall become <pb n="4"/> again a holy thing. I am astonished when I hear a woman vindicate the <persName ref="#Queen_Caroline">Queen</persName>. Do tell me what you think on this subject? <metamark rend="waves"/><note resp="#lmw">These wavy lines appear to represent a change in paragraph and subject (and in this case also a change from one day's writing to a later one). It seems possible that <persName ref="#MRM">Mitford </persName>uses this metamark to indicate such a change without wasting the space incurred by a paragraph break.</note></p>
            <p><date when="1820-09-13">Sept. 13.</date>--Since writing the above I have spent a day at <placeName ref="#Coley_Berks">Coley</placeName> &amp; extracted from <persName ref="#Monck_JB">Mr. Monck</persName> rather more of the Royal Visit than his wife could do, partly by cross-examination--&amp; partly from an effect of character. <said who="#Monck_JB">"You are bad enough, <persName ref="#MRM">Mary</persName>,"</said> <del rend="squiggles">said</del> quoth he <said who="#Monck_JB">"but not quite so bitter as my wife."</said> She really did speak to them--She said <said who="#Queen_Caroline">"You do me honour--it is an excellent address"</said>--(I dare say she thought so for of all the fulsome nonsense that has been penned on her none this surpassed!)--her presence was announced by a prodigious giggling chattering &amp; romping outside the door--like a parcel of boys let loose from school--which suddenly ceased &amp; she entered as gravely as <persName ref="#Liston_SarahT">Mrs. Liston</persName> in <bibl corresp="#TomThumb_OHaraAdpt"><persName ref="#Queen_Dollalolla">Queen Dollalolla</persName></bibl>.<note resp="#ebb #lmw"><persName ref="#Liston_SarahT">Mitford is conflating a celebrated role in a burletta with the production itself: Sarah Tyrer Liston, as Sarah Tyrer</persName> before her marriage in <date when="1807">1807</date>, was widely celebrated for her performance of <persName ref="#Queen_Dollalolla">Queen Dollalolla</persName> in <bibl corresp="#TomThumb_OHaraAdpt">a comic opera adaptation of <title ref="#TomThumb_Fielding">Tom Thumb</title></bibl>. She continued her acting career as <persName ref="#Liston_SarahT">Mrs. Liston</persName> until <date when="1822">1822</date>.</note> Her dress we had a great deal of fun about from the delicious ignorance of the describer. It was in the midst of the Court mourning &amp; he put himself to charges for a black suit, the coat he had to go to <orgName ref="#Pius7_Court">the Pope's Court</orgName><note resp="#ebb">If <persName ref="#Monck_JB">Monck</persName> paid a visit to the Pope's Court, presumably this was <orgName ref="#Pius7_Court">the court of <persName ref="#Pius7_Pope">Pope Pius VII</persName> of <date from="1800" to="1823">1800-1823</date></orgName>. <persName ref="#Napoleon">Napoleon</persName> forced <orgName ref="#Pius7_Court"><persName ref="#Pius7_Pope">the Pope</persName> and his Cardinals</orgName> into exile to <placeName ref="#Savona">the province of Savona</placeName> <date from="1809" to="1813">between 1809 and 1813</date>, but was restored to <placeName ref="#Rome">Rome</placeName> by signing a treaty. It seems likely that <persName ref="#Monck_JB">Monck</persName> would have visited <orgName ref="#Pius7_Court">the Pope's Court</orgName> during his time in <placeName ref="#Europe">Europe</placeName> in the previous decade.</note> being unluckily of a pure colour--but <rs type="person" ref="#Queen_Caroline">the Lady herself</rs> was it appears in colours--<said who="#Monck_JB">"fawn Colour <persName ref="#MRM">Mary</persName>--the colour of that Cow!"</said>--<said who="#MRM" direct="false">How was it made:</said> <gap unit="word" quantity="1" reason="deletion"/><del rend="squiggles" unit="word" quantity="1"> .</del> <said who="#Monck_JB">"So"</said>--buttoning up his Coat--<said who="#MRM" direct="false">Of a Man's Coat--pray was the best of her apparel</said>--<said who="#Monck_JB">"Don't be foolish--a woman's coat"--a grey coat--the thing you all wear in winter"</said> <said who="#MRM" direct="false">--a Pelisse?--</said> <said who="#Monck_JB">"Yes--a fawn coloured pelisse--garnished with gold!"</said>--<metamark rend="waves"/></p>
            <p>Have you read <title ref="#Abbot_WS">the Abbot</title>?  I have just finished it--disappointed--because as every alternate book of his is commonly excellent &amp; the last was bad I had made up my mind that this should be good--&amp; good it would be from <choice><sic>any body</sic><reg resp="#lmw">anybody</reg></choice> else, but he has accustomed us to such writing that mere mediocrity will not satisfy us. After all it is remarkably pleasant reading--quite as free from the peculiar faults as the striking beauties of the <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Author</persName>--no ghost--no prophecies--only one old woman &amp; not much of her--&amp; no torture scene--a very agreeable book, but <pb n="5"/> not one which as a first work would have made a reputation like <title ref="#Waverley">Waverley</title> or <title ref="#Old_Mortality">Old Mortality</title>.--The great fault of the story is that the subject is in fact a bad one. <persName ref="#MaryQoS">Mary Queen of Scots</persName> is a person of whom with all her sins we have dreamt all our life long<choice><sic>--</sic><reg>. </reg></choice>There is not a creature of any imagination who has not made her romance in his own mind long before now--the <persName ref="#MaryQoS">Bodleian Mary</persName> all beauty &amp; all grace, the love of all men--the envy of all women--She who makes possible all that has been feigned of nymph or Goddess--there is no writing up to what one fancies of Her! Nobody has ever accomplished this feat--no one ever will--<persName ref="#Schiller_F">Schiller</persName>--<persName ref="#Alfieri_Vittorio">Alfieri</persName>--<persName ref="#Hogg_J">the Ettrick Shepherd</persName>--three Master Spirits have all failed when they wrote of <persName ref="#MaryQoS">Queen Mary</persName>--but I think the failure of <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Walter Scott</persName> the most egregious of any--he takes her down from her pedestal--makes her scold--disenchants <persName ref="#Dulcinea_DQ">the lady Dulcinea del Toboso</persName>--wakens one from one's pleasant dream--brings a light befo<gap reason="torn" unit="chars" quantity="2"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">re</supplied></unclear><note resp="#ebb">At the end of this line and the next, a couple of characters have been obliterated by the removal of the seal.</note> one's magic lantern &amp; puts out the pretty pictures--Now th<gap reason="torn" unit="chars" quantity="2"/><unclear><supplied resp="#lmw">at</supplied></unclear> is not a friend's office--nor a poet's--as the critics I suppose will tell him. Meanwhile the book is pleasant reading in spite of this fault &amp; another--which is that all the plot which is not <persName ref="#MaryQoS">Queen Mary</persName> is occupied by a twin brother &amp; sister confusion--like the <persName ref="#Sebastian_TN">Sebastian</persName> &amp; <persName ref="#Viola_TN">Viola</persName> of <title ref="#TwelfthNight_Shkspr">Twelfth Night</title>. Now it is not wise in <persName ref="#Scott_Wal">Sir Walter Scott</persName> to remind his readers of malice prepense of <title ref="#TwelfthNight_Shkspr"><persName ref="#Shakespeare">Shakespeare</persName>'s last work</title> &amp; worthy to be his last work--moreover <persName ref="#Catherine_Ab">Catherine</persName> is as little like the delicious <persName ref="#Viola_TN">Viola</persName> as <persName ref="#Henry_Ab">Henry</persName> is like the frank &amp; generous <persName ref="#Sebastian_TN">Sebastian</persName>. Notwithstanding which the book is a pleasant book, as you will think &amp; say.<metamark rend="waves"/></p>
            <p>Have you seen <bibl corresp="#Rome_ThreeMonths_Graham">Mrs. Graham's Three Months residence in the Mountains east of Rome</bibl>? (bad overgrown title!) Very entertaining--particularly the Surgeon's escape from the Banditti--the manner in which his poor Townsmen stripped themselves of all for his ransom &amp; then went to Church in procession to thank God for his deliverance quite makes <pb n="6"/>one in love with the Italians. <persName ref="#Graham_Maria">Mrs. Graham</persName> by the way is the lady respecting whom <title ref="#QuarterlyRev_per">the Quarterly</title> some time ago made so curious a mistake. She went with her husband to <placeName ref="#India">India</placeName> &amp; published <bibl corresp="#India_JournalResidence_Graham">a Journal of her residence there</bibl>--mentioning the aforementioned husband in almost every page--but the Critic wanted a book to cut up &amp; chose Maria Graham's prefacing his review by saying <quote>"This work is we suppose the product of some young lady who went out on a matrimonial speculation &amp; having failed in that design is now come back to try the book market"</quote>--&amp; so forth.<note resp="#ebb">Mitford is almost certainly recalling the review of Graham's work likely by <persName>John Barrow</persName> published in <title>The Quarterly Review</title> as article 8 of the <date when="1812-12">December 1812</date> issue. The review begins, <quote>"'<title ref="#India_JournalResidence_Graham">The Journal of a Residence in India</title>,' by a young lady who, probably, went thither, like most young ladies, to procure a husband instead of information, is a literary curiosity which we are not disposed to overlook."</quote> On the conjectured authorship of the review, see <ref target="http://www.rc.umd.edu/reference/qr/index/16.htmlhttp://www.rc.umd.edu/reference/qr/index/16.html">The Quarterly Review Archive</ref>.</note>--My dear <persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">Sir William</persName> you must write to me soon--You will confess that I have sent you nonsense enough this bout.--Has <persName ref="#Elford_Elizabeth">Miss Elizabeth</persName> finished the roses &amp; oak boughs? (You see I have not had a chat with <persName ref="#Palmer_Mad">Lady Madelina</persName> for nothing!) Has <persName ref="#Elford_Grace">Miss Elford</persName> recovered her parrot?--&amp; above all Does Miss Welsford's<note resp="#lmw #ebb">We have not identified Miss Welsford, but speculate that she might be a friend of Sir William's daughters.</note> health continue to improve?--Kindest regards from all here.--</p><closer>Ever my dear friend<lb/> Most sincerely &amp; affectionately your's <signed>M.R. Mitford</signed>
            
 <address>
<addrLine><placeName ref="#Reading_city">Reading</placeName> <date when="1820-09-15">September fifteen 1820</date></addrLine>
<addrLine><persName ref="#Elford_SirWm">S<hi rend="superscript">r</hi> W<hi rend="superscript">m</hi> Elford Bar<hi rend="superscript">t</hi></persName></addrLine>
<addrLine>Bickham</addrLine>
 <addrLine><persName ref="#Monck_JB">J. B. Monck</persName>--<placeName ref="#Plymouth_city">Plymouth</placeName></addrLine>
  </address>
         </closer>
              

         </div>
      </body>
    
     <back>
       
          <!--ebb: 1 February 2015: Added new prosopography from the last page of the letter to the site index.-->
     <!--ebb:1 July 2014: Added prosopography to the site index, and wrote new prosop entries from this letter-->
      <!--ebb: 29 May 2014: New prosop. from this letter entered into site index.-->
     </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
