
<?xml-model href="../Parker_NellNelsonProject_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <div type="newspaperArticle">
        <head>
            <newspaperTitle>Chicago Times
                <date when="1888-08-02">Morning, August 2, 1888</date>.
                Price <num type="price" amount=".02">2 Cents</num>
            </newspaperTitle>
            <seriesTitle>City Slave Girls</seriesTitle>

            <headLine>“The Times” Lady Reporter, in the Guise of a Factory Bondwoman, Is Insulted by
                a Scoundrel.</headLine>
            <headLine>Accosted by a Well-Dressed Brute Who Tries to Thrust His Blighting Friendship
                on Her.</headLine>
            <headLine><desc of="upperClass">Human Monsters Who Lure from Virtue’s Path</desc> the
                    <desc of="workingClass">Half-Starved Victims of Man’s
                Cupidity</desc>.</headLine>
            <headLine>
                <workingConditions category="wageDesc">Manufacturers Who Pay Their Serfs the Miserly
                    Sum of <num type="wage" amount=".80">Eighty Cents</num> for Making a Dozen
                        <factoryItem>Shirts</factoryItem>.</workingConditions>
            </headLine>
            <headLine>A Big Collar and Cad Maker of Troy N.Y Astonished at the State of Affairs in
                    <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName>.</headLine>
        </head>
        <articleBody>On Thursday morning when I started to renew my factory life I discovered after
            getting on a South-side car that I did not have a cent in my pocket. In putting on my
            shop-girl disguise I had left my purse at home. When the conductor asked for the fair I
            had none to give him. It was very hot, the clouds threatened rain, and the shop was at
            so great a distance that I did not feel as if I could walk. I concluded to throw myself
            on the generosity of <person gender="male">the conductor</person> and told him I had
            forgotten my purse. He looked ugly and told me to get off. Just as he placed his whistle
            to his lips to signal the gripman to stop a <person gender="male">distinguished,
                well-dressed man</person> paid my fare. I thanked him for his courtesy and told him
            if he would give me his card I would send him the money he had so kindly paid. He smiled
            and said:<mascVoice connotation="positive"> “A mere bagatelle miss, and not worth
                mentioning.”</mascVoice> At<location type="streetName"> Eighteenth street</location>
            I left the car to go to a vestmaker’s place at <location type="address">2155 Archer
                avenue</location>. I was crossing the three points where <location type="streetName"
                >State and Nineteenth streets intersect</location> when who should come abreast but
            my benefactor. <desc of="upperClass">Instead of raising his hat he jauntily cocked his
                left eye and came so close to me that the sleeve of my “never-rip” jersey was
                pressed against the waist-line of his light-gray suit.</desc>
            <dialogue><mascVoice connotation="sexual">“Aha, here we are again!”</mascVoice> Although
                I distinctly heard every word of his remark I said: <nellVoice
                    connotation="offended">“I beg your pardon,”</nellVoice> with as much of the
                Newport chill as I could affect. <mascVoice connotation="sexual">“Come, come,
                    now,”</mascVoice> he said with increased gayety, moving his waistband still
                closer to my jersey. <nellVoice connotation="sarcasmWit">“Oh, you are the gentleman
                    to whom I am indebted for car-fare. You want your money I suppose; if you will
                    give me your card I will write you an order.”</nellVoice>
                <mascVoice>“Do you work in this neighborhood?”</mascVoice>
                <nellVoice>“No sir.”</nellVoice>
                <mascVoice>“Where, then?”</mascVoice>
                <nellVoice>“No place.”</nellVoice>
                <mascVoice>“Where are you going?”</mascVoice>
                <nellVoice>“For work.”</nellVoice>
                <mascVoice>“What kind?”</mascVoice>
                <nellVoice>“Any kind. May I have your card? I am in something of a
                    hurry.”</nellVoice>
                <mascVoice>“Mayn’t I have yours?”</mascVoice> he asked. <nellVoice
                    connotation="sarcasmWit">“Certainly; I haven’t my case, but if you will lend me
                    a pencil I will write you one.”</nellVoice>
                <mascVoice connotation="sexual">“With pleasure, my dear.”</mascVoice>
                <nellVoice connotation="sarcasmWit">“You are mistaken, sir. That is not my
                    name.”</nellVoice>
                <mascVoice connotation="sexual">“Ha, ha, ha! I see you are a little mischievous, but
                    for all that you are my dear,”</mascVoice> producing three inches of Faber.
                    <nellVoice connotation="sarcasmWit">“A card please?”</nellVoice>
                <mascVoice>“Bless me, I had forgotten,”</mascVoice> and the natty-sack-coat was
                ransacked for a suitable card. <mascVoice>“Ah, here—this will do, I hope, in lieu of
                    something more conventional,”</mascVoice> carefully placing on my sewing-box a
                small card with the address down. I reversed the pasteboard and read on the back:
                    <persName>DR. Charles Gilman Smith.</persName> Office Hours _________
                Residence___________ <nellVoice>“<persName>Dr. Smith</persName>! I know him quite
                    well.”</nellVoice>
                <mascVoice connotation="negative">“Oh, you do, eh?”</mascVoice> in a tone that left
                no doubt that his stock in me had dropped. I wrote: <nellVoice
                    connotation="sarcasmWit">Reporter. <ref to="theTimes">The
                    Times.</ref></nellVoice> and handed it to my companion, who read it with eyes
                that seemed to have been wired open. While he crushed the doctor’s card in his left
                hand his right pulled out a splendid gold watch, and with a most abrupt <mascVoice
                    connotation="intimidated">“Didn’t think it was so late, have an engagement at
                    9:45,”</mascVoice> was off with more alacrity than is conducive to grace. I
                looked after him, admiring the cut of his coat, the swing of his trousers, the
                polish of his shoes, and the magnificent carriage of head and shoulders, and
                thought: <nellVoice connotation="prayer">“May the lord deliver us working
                    girls.”</nellVoice></dialogue> I also thought that I should like to meet my car
            friend when I had my suffocating well off and my good clothes on. Won’t <persName>Dr.
                Smith</persName> inveigle him to his <location type="streetName">State
                street</location> office and present me? I was to give him back his nickel and lead
            pencil. When I reached the shop at <location type="address">2155 Archer
                avenue</location> the tailor told me he only wanted one
                <occupation>vestmaker</occupation> and had hired her two hours ago, I then went over
            on <location type="streetName">Cottage Grove avenue</location>, borrowed <num
                type="cost" amount=".25">25 cents</num> from my dressmaker and rode down to
                <location type="streetName">Lake street</location> to get work in a <company
                name="unidentified">feather duster factory</company>. There may have been work, but
            there was no elevator and I was too hot and tired to go up five flights of stairs to
            look for it. I chose a <company name="unidentified">cigar factory</company> on <location
                type="streetName">Randolph near Dearborn street</location> with but three pairs of
            stairs to climb and learned in the salesroom that they had all the help they needed. I
            tried <persName>Gomez</persName> across the street, who had no work, but enough goodness
            of heart to give me a chair and a letter to two cigarmakers of his nationality. I went
            to see <persName>F. Garcia</persName> at <location type="address">20th Clark
                street</location>. He asked me if I could “strip” and I told him I could. When he
            wanted to know where I had worked I owned up that I didn’t know anything at all about
            the business but was anxious to learn and get work. He didn’t know <mascVoice>“how a
                sewing girl would do at the ‘fillers’ but you might go and talk with some of the
                help, for you may not be satisfied to try even.”</mascVoice> He showed me the way
            across the hall to an empty room. <workingConditions category="negative">The floor was
                littered with rags and paper and the dust was heavy on the walls and wood-work and
                in one corner was a good-sized ash-pile</workingConditions>.
                <persName>Garcia</persName> rapped for entrance, but there was so much noise within
            that the door remained fast. When the <nationality nation="Spain">Spaniard</nationality>
            left me I turned the knob and came upon <workingConditions category="negative">a big boy
                who was tickling his laborers. The girls were flying around the empty room and their
                pursuer had both screeching. The fun came to a stop the moment I went
                in</workingConditions> and the young people gladly told me all I cared to know about
            the business. All they did was to “strip” – just pull the stem or mid-rib from the leaf
            and put it in a “book-filler.” <workingConditions category="wageDesc">I could get <num
                    type="wage" amount="4.00">$4</num> a week and steady work and the next year <num
                    type="wage" amount="5.00">$5</num>.</workingConditions>
            <person who="workingGirl" gender="female">My informant, a little girl of 15 years, has
                been in the shop two years and earned <num type="wage" amount="5.30">$5.30</num> a
                week. She told me she was the oldest hand in the shop: that she could “strip” as
                fast as a man, and put the ribbon bands about the cigars before they were
                boxed.</person>
            <workingConditions category="workDesc">At 12:15 o’clock I went into the shop and was
                given a chair in front of a barrel filled with inches of tobacco called “hands” and
                lined with gunny-cloth. There was a little tin pail of brown water for wetting I
                don’t know what near my chair, and on the other side a pine board three feet long
                and sixteen inches wide. When the tobacco leaves were stripped and laid on the board
                it was thubbed a “book-filler” and carried off to the next room. In the shop with
                this were some eighteen men or more rolling the “fillers,” putting on the wrappers,
                shaping the cigars with a broad knife and seeming the ends.</workingConditions>
            Along the tables some of the men were smoking and others chewing, some with their hats
            on and all in the shirt-sleeves. <desc of="workingClass">There were <nationality
                    nation="Africa">negroes</nationality>, <nationality nation="Sweden"
                    >Swedes</nationality>, a <nationality nation="China">Chinaman</nationality>,
                    <nationality nation="Germany">Germans</nationality>, and <nationality
                    nation="Spain">Spaniards</nationality>, whose influence on the lives of the
                young girls, while not really harmful, could hardly be called beneficial.</desc> I
            stripped leaves enough to enable me to take the social condition of the inmates,
                <workingConditions category="negative">the bad light impure
                atmosphere</workingConditions>, <workingConditions category="negative">the choking
                smell of the tobacco</workingConditions>, and the photographs and prints cut from
            sensational papers that were tacked on the <workingConditions category="negative"
                >smoke-stained walls</workingConditions>. From the <company name="unidentified"
                >cigar factory</company> I went to the <company name="identified">Excelsior
                Underwear Company</company>, <location type="address">199 and 201 Fifth
                avenue</location> and sat for half an hour while the <person who="forePerson"
                gender="female">forewoman</person> scolded a <person who="workingGirl"
                gender="female">pale-faced girl who wore mourning</person>. She had brought back a
            dozen chemises for which the house paid <num type="wage" amount="2.00">$2</num>, but the
            work was soiled in the making—machine oil having wet the cotton – and the forewoman
            refused to take it. <dialogue><femVoice who="workingGirl" connotation="woe">“What shall
                    I do?”</femVoice> She asked the woman, with a voice as sad as her face.
                    <femVoice who="forePerson" connotation="angry">“What does anybody do with dirty
                    things? You will have to pay for laundering the garments of the greasy sewing
                    and clean the thread.”</femVoice></dialogue> Then the <person who="workingGirl"
                gender="female">girl</person> was left alone by the <person who="forePerson"
                >manager</person>, who went up to the other end of the counter to get trimmings for
            six dozen <factoryItem>chemises</factoryItem> that a tall young <nationality
                nation="Sweden">Swede</nationality> girl was waiting for. <desc of="upperClass">The
                forewoman wore a blue dress of plaid design with a Marseilles vest buttoned in it,
                and of seven rings on her left hand six were set with what appeared to be diamonds.
                She had jewels at her chin and in her ears and hair.</desc> She measured off the
            lace edgings and the tape insertion and gave minute directions about the fullness and
            the finish. The six dozen garments were bundled up by <persName>Mr. Hyman</persName>,
            the proprietor, and the elevator carried her and her load to the pavement below.
                <livingConditions category="descriptionNeutral">The seamstress told me she lived at
                home</livingConditions> and <workingConditions category="wageDesc">with the help of
                her mother made <num type="wage" amount="12.00">$12</num> a
            week</workingConditions>. <dialogue><femVoice>“It is very hard work though,”</femVoice>
                she said <femVoice>"We sew day and night. I had rather do it than work down in a
                    shop for I have more self-respect. <desc of="workingClass">All the girls are not
                        good, and very few are in a position to go with respectable people. They go
                        with bad company and their language is bad. Sometimes in the winter they
                        dance till daylight and go from the hall to the shop. I don’t blame them.
                        The life of a girl who had nothing to depend on but her needle is a best a
                        hard one.</desc> Still I don’t like to be with a crowd of factory girls if I
                    can help it. <workingConditions category="negative">The manager and
                        superintendent obliged to be strict</workingConditions>, but <desc
                        of="upperClass">very seldom make any distinction in the treatment of a nice
                        girl and one who is not so nice. I don’t think I can tell you how many ways
                        there are to insult a girl. I have had a foreman just give me a look as I
                        passed in to my machine or handed in my sewing that made me wish I was
                        dead.</desc>
                    <workingConditions category="negative">Then there are the spiteful things the
                        girls say about you and the cutting remarks of the forewoman that make you
                        feel like fainting.</workingConditions>
                    <workingConditions category="negative">The cashier may have a grudge and if he
                        doesn’t hold your wages back till all the other hands are paid hell will
                        throw it at you, make you take ragged bills, or give – ‘you a week’s pay in
                        change.’</workingConditions> A cashier in a <location type="streetName"
                        >Jackson street</location>
                    <company name="unidentified">cravat factory</company> once rubbed his hand
                    across my chin <mascVoice connotation="sexual">“to feel my
                        whiskers,”</mascVoice> he said, and <workingConditions category="negative"
                        >because I got angry and said I would report him he saved up all the silver
                        that had holes and plugs and made me take it</workingConditions>.
                        <workingConditions category="wageDesc">My salary was <num type="wage"
                            amount="3.25">$3.25</num> that week, and some of the silver couldn’t
                        pass. I took it to a bank and the cashier was kind enough to give me good
                        money for it.</workingConditions> Plenty of times the forewoman has had me
                    discharged for being “stuck up.”</femVoice></dialogue>
            <workingConditions category="wageDesc"> Prices here range from <num type="wage"
                    amount=".20">20 cents</num> to <num type="price" amount="2.00">$2</num> a dozen.
                It depends on the material. <factoryItem>Children’s drawers</factoryItem> pay <num
                    type="wage" amount=".20">20 cents</num> a dozen, but there are no button holes
                to work. Some shirts are <num type="price" amount="2.00">$2</num> some <num
                    type="price" amount="4.00">$4</num> and some <num type="price" amount="1.70"
                    >$1.70</num> but most of them only pay <num type="wage" amount=".20">20
                    cents</num>. Everything is done by machine including button holes and gussets.
                The bosoms and bands are ready to go in. <factoryItem>Corset-covers</factoryItem>
                pay <num type="wage" amount=".40">40 cents</num>and
                    <factoryItem>chemises</factoryItem>
                <num type="wage" amount=".20">20 cents</num> each, but they have to be trimmed and
                the holes worked by hand. This is a mean shop, so far as prices go, but they are all
                alike in that particular.</workingConditions>
            <workingConditions category="negative">You have to find your own
                thread</workingConditions> and <workingConditions category="negative">you are
                constantly being suspected of keeping back short ends of
                trimmings</workingConditions>. I asked the <person who="forePerson" gender="female"
                >forewoman</person> for stitching and was given <factoryItem>shirts</factoryItem> at
                <num type="wage" amount=".80">80 cents</num> a dozen to do. I had to pay <num
                type="cost" amount=".50">50 cents</num> for the use of the machine and <num
                type="cost" amount=".25">25 cents</num> for a spindle of thread. I told the
            forewoman I had left my purse at home, but she said it was <femVoice who="forePerson"
                >“alright you can have it taken out of your wages."</femVoice> I asked her what the
            machine cost, but she doesn’t know, and when I ventured that the expiration of the
            patient had reduced the old place <num type="cost" amount="15.00">$15</num> to about
                <num type="cost" amount="12.00">$12</num> she told me she <femVoice>“reckoned I
                didn’t know what I was talking about.”</femVoice>
            <workingConditions category="descriptionNeutral">The room where we worked was about
                eighteen feet wide and ten feet deep with toilet closets built out from the walls.
                The machines encircled the three walls and in the middle of the floor were the boxes
                of work.</workingConditions>
            <workingConditions category="wageDesc">One girl was stitching wrist-bands, another had
                button-hole machine and was getting <num type="wage" amount=".50">50 cents</num> a
                hundred. A third was making <factoryItem>tucked drawers</factoryItem> at <num
                    type="wage" amount=".20">20 cents</num> a dozen and I had a
                    <factoryItem>shirt</factoryItem> at <num type="wage" amount=".60">60 cents</num>
                which I failed to finish all three hours, being unable to manage a
                machine.</workingConditions> -<ref to="nellNelson">Nell Nelson</ref>. </articleBody>
    </div>
</root>
