<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="nll_2016-01-17_RNGSchema_Exercise2.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<document type="personalLetter">
    <head><date when="1852-06-11">June 11, 1852</date></head>
    <body>
        <p>I have but one thought, <persName ref="#susie">Susie</persName>, this <timeOfDay type="afternoon">afternoon</timeOfDay> of <month class="June">June</month>, and that of you, and I have one prayer, only; dear <persName ref="#susie">Susie</persName>, that is for you. That you and I in hand as we e'en do in heart, might ramble away as children, among the woods and fields, and forget these many years, and these sorrowing cares, and each become a child again -- I would it were so, <persName ref="#susie">Susie</persName>, and when I look around me and find myself alone, I sigh for you again; little sigh, and vain sigh, which will not bring you home.</p>
        <p>I need you more and more, and the great world grows wider, and dear ones fewer and fewer, every day that you stay away -- I miss my biggest heart; my own goes wandering round, and calls for <persName ref="#susie">Susie</persName> -- Friends are too dear to sunder, Oh they are far too few, and how soon they will go away where you and I cannot find them, don't let us forget these things, for their remembrance now will save us many an anguish when it is too late to love them! <persName ref="#susie">Susie</persName>, forgive me Darling, for every word I say -- my heart is full of you, none other than you is in my thoughts, yet when I seek to say to you something not for the world, words fail me. If you were here -- and Oh that you were, my <persName ref="#susie">Susie</persName>, we need not talk at all, our eyes would whisper for us, and your hand fast in mine, we would not ask for language -- I try to bring you nearer, I chase the weeks away till they are quite departed, and fancy you have come, and I am on my way through the green lane to meet you, and my heart goes scampering so, that I have much ado to bring it back again, and learn it to be patient, till that dear <persName ref="#susie">Susie</persName> comes. Three weeks -- they can't last always, for surely they must go with their little brothers and sisters to their long home in the <placeName type="continent" continent="North_America">west</placeName>!</p>
        <p>I shall grow more and more impatient until that dear day comes, for till now, I have only mourned for you; now I begin to hope for you.</p>
        <p>Dear <persName ref="#susie">Susie</persName>, I have tried hard to think what you would love, of something I might send you -- I at last say my little Violets, they begged me to let them go, so here they are -- and with them as Instructor, a bit of knightly grass, who also begged the favor to accompany them -- they are but small, <persName ref="#susie">Susie</persName>, and I fear not fragrant now, but they will speak to you of warm hearts at home, and of something faithful which "<quote>never slumbers nor sleeps</quote>" -- Keep them 'neath your pillow, <persName ref="#susie">Susie</persName>, they will make you dream of blue-skies, and home, and the "<quote>blessed contrie</quote>"! You and I will have an hour with "<quote><persName ref="#edward">Edward</persName></quote>" and "<quote><persName ref="#em">Ellen Middleton</persName></quote>", sometime when you get home -- we must find out if some things contained therein are true, and if they are, what you and me are coming to!</p>
    </body>
    <closing>
        Now, farewell, <persName ref="#susie">Susie</persName>, and <persName ref="#vinnie">Vinnie</persName> sends her love, and mother her's, and I add a kiss, shyly, lest there is somebody there! Don't let them see, will you <persName ref="#susie">Susie</persName>?
    </closing>
    <signature><persName ref="#ed">Emilie</persName> --</signature>
    <postScript>
        <p>Why can't I be the delegate to the great <orgName type="nomination" when="1852">Whig Convention</orgName>? -- don't I know all about <persName ref="#dw">Daniel Webster</persName>, and the Tariff, and the Law? Then, <persName ref="#susie">Susie</persName> I could see you, during a pause in the session -- but I don't like this country at all, and I shan't stay here any longer! "<quote language="Latin">Delenda est</quote>" <placeName type="continent" continent="North_America">America</placeName>, <placeName type="state" state="Massachusetts">Massachusetts</placeName> and all!</p>
        <p>open me carefully</p>
    </postScript>
</document>
