
<?xml-model href="../Parker_NellNelsonProject_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <div type="newspaperArticle">

        <head>
            <newspaperTitle>Chicago Times
                <date when="1888-08-03">Morning, August 3, 1888</date>
                Price <num type="price" amount=".02">2 Cents</num>
            </newspaperTitle>

            <seriesTitle>City Slave Girls</seriesTitle>

            <headLine>While Among <placeName type="city">Chicago</placeName>’s Weak Serfs <ref
                    to="nellNelson">The Times’ Lady Reporter</ref> Finds <persName>Mr.
                    Goss</persName>’ “Good <nationality nation="undefined"
                >Jew</nationality>.”</headLine>

            <headLine>Holding Her Nose, She Gazes Upon All Kinds of <desc of="workingClass"
                    >Soul-and-Body Starving Wretchedness</desc>.</headLine>
            <headLine><workingConditions category="workDesc">In a Small, Dirty Room Filled with A
                    Crowd of Women</workingConditions>
                <workingConditions category="negative">Life Seems Like a Hideous
                    Dream</workingConditions>.</headLine>
            <headLine>To Save Space, These Unshackled Servants of Greed Are Compelled to Take Short
                Stitches.</headLine>
            <headLine><workingConditions category="negative">Even Pins Are Not Given to the
                    Employee</workingConditions> and the <workingConditions category="negative"
                    >Girls Have to Use Their Underclothing for
                Towels</workingConditions>.</headLine>
        </head>

        <articleBody>Two weeks ago <persName>Rev. Mr. Gross</persName> preached a sermon relative to
            the morals and progress of the working woman. Among other things he referred to a “good
            Jew” who, having the comfort of the hundred odd girls in his <company
                name="unidentified">cloak factory</company> at heart, “provided every day for <desc
                of="workingClass"><num type="cost" amount=".01">1 cent</num> a substantial
                lunch</desc>.” I sent the reverend gentleman a note, inclosing a stamp for the
            address of the “good <nationality nation="undefined">Jew</nationality>” and in reply
            came the name of <persName>H. Zimmerman</persName>, <location type="address">233 Monroe
                street</location>. On went <desc of="workingClass">poverty’s respectable
            rags</desc>, and off I posted for shop-work and a penny spread. The elevator carried me
            to the top of the building where every week thousands of
                <factoryItem>jackets</factoryItem>, <factoryItem>sacques</factoryItem>,
                <factoryItem>circulars</factoryItem>, <factoryItem>dolmans</factoryItem>, and
                <factoryItem>cloaks</factoryItem> are turned out to supply the country trade of the
            northwest. Here in a <workingConditions category="negative">crowded room, with low
                ceiling and dingy walls, poorly ventilated and insufficiently
                lighted</workingConditions>, <workingConditions category="negative">sit between
                eighty and 150 young girls surrounded from Monday morning until Saturday noon by the
                ceaseless clatter of the sewing-machines in an atmosphere so thick that it can be
                cut with a knife</workingConditions>. <workingConditions category="negative">The
                machines are run by steam, and notwithstanding the great buckram fans overhead that
                revolve with a crackling noise the ceiling is so low</workingConditions> and the
                <workingConditions category="negative">air so hot as to be positively stifling to
                the initiated</workingConditions>. There is the <workingConditions
                category="negative">smell of dye from brown, blue, and black cloaks coupled with the
                still more offensive odor from the “English plaids”</workingConditions>;
                <workingConditions category="workDesc">along the pressing-table are the gas stoves
                where irons are heated and where the girls sponge and press collars and seams, each
                operation attended with a little cloud of steam and a stuffy, scorching smell that
                blows about and around the whizzing fans</workingConditions>; <workingConditions
                category="negative">clouds of lint from the textures in hand covers everything it
                constantly being inhaled by the sewers</workingConditions>. Then, too, there is
                the<workingConditions category="negative"> smell of rancid machine
                oil</workingConditions>; the <workingConditions category="negative">overpowering
                exhalations from so many perspiring and unkempt persons and an occasional whiff from
                the six or seven toilets closets</workingConditions>, all powerful facts of one
            might smell that must be smelled to be appreciated. <workingConditions
                category="negative">The <person who="employer" gender="male">“good Jew”</person> had
                all the windows open, but the place was so strong I almost
                fainted</workingConditions>. I have a seat in the middle of the room and a <num
                type="cost" amount=".35">35 cent</num>
            <factoryItem>Norfolk</factoryItem> to make. <workingConditions category="negative">It is
                so dark that I can hardly see my stitches as I thread to sleeve hole with black
                muslin.</workingConditions> The <person who="forePerson" gender="female"
                >forewoman</person> can’t see either till she takes the work over to the window to
            examine it, and returns with a gratifying, <femVoice who="forePerson"
                connotation="positive">“Guess that it will do.”</femVoice>
            <workingConditions category="negative">We are so crowded along the line of tables that
                the girls are told to “take short threads,”</workingConditions> and
                <workingConditions category="negative">I duck my head every time the <desc
                    of="workingClass">pale-faced, hollow-eyed girl</desc> at my left pulls her
                needle out, to escape being hit</workingConditions>. She has only been able to make
            three <num type="cost" amount=".50">50 cent</num>
            <factoryItem>long cloaks</factoryItem> in five days and says: <dialogue><femVoice
                    who="workingGirl" connotation="intimidated">“You won’t mind my taking long
                    threads; will you, if I don’t hit you?”</femVoice>
                <nellVoice connotation="positive"><workingConditions category="camaraderie">I tell
                        her to pull away and offer to fell the bottom hem on her cloak to which she
                        agrees.</workingConditions></nellVoice></dialogue>
            <desc of="workingClass">She has on a cheap jersey waist, a calico skirt, and the little
                but of underwear that shows at her neck where she has opened her collar is as black
                almost as her jersey. Her shoes are broken and one of the uppers is mended with
                black thread. She lives with her folks and has “a lot of little brothers and
                sisters, but the ‘Q’ strikes have put them all out” so that she hasn’t bought
                anything for herself this year except a hat at the Fair.</desc>
            <dialogue><nellVoice connotation="prayer">“Do you go to church?”</nellVoice> I ask.
                    <femVoice who="workingGirl">“What’d I go to church for?”</femVoice>
                <!--Not sure what connotation should go with the above and below nellVoice. Could this be prayer simply because she is talkign about church? Or is descriptionnNeutral good enough?-->
                <nellVoice connotation="prayer">“For the music and the sermon.”</nellVoice>
                <femVoice who="workingGirl">“I want a seat, though, and <desc of="workingClass">I’d
                        rather ride down to the shop and back than pay <num type="price"
                            amount=".10">10 cents</num> to get in the pew</desc>.”</femVoice>
                <nellVoice connotation="pity">A poor little creature, bony and grimy, and wild-eyed
                    as the “marchioness” goes down on her hands and knees and turns out the dust in
                    the cracks of the floor with the eye of her needle.</nellVoice>
                <femVoice>“I’m huntin’ for pins,”</femVoice> she says, <femVoice>“to fix on the
                    braid.”</femVoice>
                <nellVoice connotation="descriptionNeutral">“Doesn’t <persName>Zimmerman</persName>
                    provide you with pins?”</nellVoice>
                <femVoice who="workingGirl" connotation="negative">“Indeed he doesn’t; nor with
                    nothin’ else but fannin’ and what’s the good of fans in an
                oven?”</femVoice></dialogue> The child turns up the pins some of them bent, and puts
            them first in her mouth to straighten them and then in the bosom of her dress <femVoice
                who="workingGirl" connotation="prayer">humming to herself, “Rock of
                Ages.”</femVoice> At the expiration of the hunt a new difficulty befalls her. The
            needle’s eye is stuffed as she says and in an effort to remove the filling off goes the
            head optic and all. <workingConditions category="camaraderie">Nobody has another to lend
                and I give her mine.</workingConditions> She says she is <persName>Pat</persName>
            and the daughter of a <location type="streetName">Twelfth street</location> teamster.
            Her mother is living and <livingConditions category="descriptionNeutral">she and her
                brother <femVoice who="workingGirl">“help the family
                along.”</femVoice></livingConditions>
            <femVoice who="workingGirl" connotation="negative">“Yes, I went to school and learned
                numbers and geography, but I can’t sew very well. <workingConditions
                    category="wageDesc">The <person who="forePerson" gender="female"
                        >forelady</person> says that’s why I don’t make more. I got <num type="wage"
                        amount="2.75">$2.75</num> one week, but I don’t know how much I’ll earn this
                    week. I used to be in the Fair and they gave me <num type="wage" amount="2"
                        >$2</num> runnin’—checks</workingConditions> I didn’t like it there, because
                I never got home till 8 at night and the boys was guyin’ us all the
                time.”</femVoice> At noon time <workingConditions category="negative">the girls
                crowded into the wash-room and those unable to reach the already wrining-wet towel
                that hung near the sink dried on their dresses.</workingConditions> I saw a tall
            young <nationality nation="Germany">German</nationality> woman wash her arms and neck
            and shake off the water as well as she could with the palms of her hands before putting
            on her dress waist again. Another, a girl of 14, who wore a plaid skirt and an old
            velvet jacket, dried her hands on her underclothing. <workingConditions
                category="negative">The lunch the <person who="employer" gender="male">“good
                    Jew”</person> served consisted of a cup of black coffee that was neither
                nutritious nor fragrant, and minus cream and sugar, for which the girls paid <num
                    type="cost" amount=".2">2 cents</num> a cup. Then there were cuts of pie at <num
                    type="cost" amount=".5">5 cents</num>each, which delicacy, architecturally
                speaking, had two stories, substantially built, with a water-proof inner lining of
                fruit mucilage. The top crust had bubbled up in the baking till it was a warty as
                tripe, and tenacity of the under dough would have sufficed for hinging a cellar
                door.</workingConditions>
            <nellVoice connotation="sarcasmWit">This is certainly not the lunch <persName>Rev. Mr.
                    Gross</persName> referred to in his sermon, but it’s the only one the girls in
                the <company name="identified"><persName>Zimmerman</persName> factory</company> knew
                anything about. </nellVoice>
            <nellVoice connotation="offended">However profitable the menu may have been to the firm
                it was anguish to many of the hungry toilers unable to procure it.</nellVoice>
            <desc of="workingClass">We girls who had no money to invest in the appetizing (?) viands
                sat by, begging with our eyes and following with melting mouths every morsel on its
                way down the throats of our neighbors.</desc>
            <desc of="workingClass">One of us, a mite of a girl, wan-faced and hectic, who had been
                watching the mastication of a well-fed machine-hand, waited till the leathery
                strangle of peach-paste had almost disappeared and then asked to consumer to
                    <femVoice who="workingGirl" connotation="woe">“give her the
                crust.”</femVoice></desc> When the well-fed party said “naw” the child called her a
            “dirty beggar” and laid her little head on her arm for a nap. <workingConditions
                category="wageDesc">I went out to buy a needle and some day when it rains and the
                wind is never weary I shall send in a bill for the <num type="wage" amount=".20">20
                    cents</num>
                <persName>H. Zimmerman</persName> owes me on a cotton-back
                Norfolk.</workingConditions>
            <workingConditions category="negative">Only a half hour was allowed for the noon rest
                during which the girls washed and combed, trimmed their finger-nails with scissors,
                and talked, or went to sleep.</workingConditions>
            <workingConditions category="negative">All hands were on deck at 7:30 in the morning, in
                which manner and the 5:30 hour of closing the Saturday half-hour was made good to
                the firm.</workingConditions> Many of the girls told me they made ten
                <factoryItem>cloaks</factoryItem> a week which averaged <num type="cost"
                amount=".30">30 cents</num> apiece. <workingConditions category="positive">Work was
                good, the season covering 10 months of the year.</workingConditions>
            <workingConditions category="negative">A number of men at work on the <factoryItem>long
                    cloaks</factoryItem> had chairs at the side of the girls and knew well enough
                personally I did not polish them for they were saturated with tobacco fumes and
                smelled a foul, sweaty, sickening odor. </workingConditions> -Nell
            Nelson</articleBody>
        <!--SD: The end of this article scan featured what seemed to be letter's to the editor with reactions to this series. Coding them in the future may prove useful to the site and to the project as a whole.-->
    </div>
</root>
