<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../Parker_NellNelsonProject_schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <div type="newspaperArticle">
        <head>
            <newspaperTitle> Chicago Times
                <date when="1888-07-31">Monday Morning, July 31, 1888</date>
                Price <num type="price" amount=".02">2 CENTS</num>
            </newspaperTitle>

            <seriesTitle>CITY SLAVE GIRLS</seriesTitle>
            <headLine>Further Details of the Factory Investigation Conducted by "The Times'" Lady
                Reporter.</headLine>

            <headLine>A Cloak Concern Where Nothing but Fear of the Law Seems to Prevent the Use of
                Lash.</headLine>

            <headLine>A Sickly Child of Fifteen Compelled to Work Nine and a Half Hours for Sixteen
                Cents.</headLine>

            <headLine>The Unfortunate Insulted and Abused by Their Employer and Humiliated by the
                Forewoman.</headLine>

            <headLine>Eighty Cents a Week for Laboring from 7:30 in the Morning Until 5:30 in the
                Evening.</headLine>
        </head>

        <articleBody> I did not realize the ignominios position of respectable poverty till I went
            to Ellinger's cloak factory, 282 Madison street, where labor is bondage, the laborer a
            slave, and flesh and blood cheaper than needles and thread. Corporations said to be
            without heart, but this concern is a commercial inquisition. It puts its help on the
            plane of slavery and nothing but civil law prevents the use of the lash. The factory is
            on the third floor of the large brick building at the east end of Madison street bridge
            on the south side of the street. Elevator? Not much. An elevator is a luxury and
            luxuries have no place at Ellinger's. You will be short of breath when you reach the top
            of the fourth flight, but in recovering you have time to take in the surroundings -- a
            great barn of a place, with the single charm of good, light. There is plenty of vacant
            room, but the women are huddled together, elbows touching, along the line of machines.
            Beneath the west windows flows the river; at the south end of the room, not ten feet
            from the crowded table, is a tier of closets, and on hot days the combined odor of the
            two is shocking. Nobody in his employ dare complain about smells, cold, heat, work,
            wages, or rules. But whoever heard of martyrs complaining? My experience began at 7:30
            a.m. and lasted just three hours. When I climbed the dusty stairs I took a ten-minute
            rest at the top. Everybody was at work but a hungry-looking man about 27 years old, with
            skin the color of a Russia turnip and thin, peaked features. He was dressed in a pair of
            heelless slippers, a white shirt, and a pair of short pants that Willonghby, Hill &amp;
            Co. pay 18 cents for making. Neither collar, vest, coat, nor suspenders burdened his
            emaciated form. He moved among the workers with a cat-like tread, his shoulders drooping
            and his knees opening and shutting with a sort of accordion movement at every step. He
            passed me several times as I stood at the desk and eyed me so unpleasantly that I turned
            my back to him. After waiting at the desk for three-quarters of an hour I asked the
            clerk, a sweet little girl of 16 years, with pretty red cheeks and dark eyelashes and
            hair, for work, and was told to wait till the forelady came round. A dozen girls were
            waiting, too, some with cloaks, others with check-books and tickets, and a few with
            hand-made fringe. The fringe-girl I spoke to. She told me she received 5 cents a yard
            for making an imitation of seal-ball fringe, such as winter cloaks are trimmed with. She
            had a piece three yards and a quarter long that had taken her all the previous day to
            make. Here was a child of 15 working nine and a half hours a day for a competence of 16
            <unclear/> cents. Will the Prairie avenue woman who, at the suggestion of Mrs. Ormison
            Chant, is trying to find one hundred girls who are earning less than 28 cents a days
            please enter Maggie W--- on the list, and will the women of the Protective agency, who
            want a new field of inquiry, call and see this slim, snake-gaited, jaundice-faced
            creature who has charge of this human mill. Maggie's fringe being measured and her book
            checked she was given another box of material and went off to weave it into
            tasel-trimming. The girl who took her place would not be interviewed. She "didn't know
            how much stitchers earned and wouldn't tell nobody how much a week she could make." She
            was, possibly, 25 years old, with a deathly pale face, and looked as though she hadn't
            eaten any breakfast. Her successor was less reticent. "I'm here since May, but I don't
            like it; the boss is a horrid thing. Him and the forelady watchs us all the time, and
            they don't give us hardly any work. I can only make one cloak a day: some pays 30 cents,
            some 40 cents, and some 50 cents. Yesterday I had only 60 cents coming to me for two
            days. Are you long here? Oh, you won't stay. They search your bag and your pocket when
            you go home nights to see if you have any thread or pieces about you." Before I had a
            chance to talk with another unfortunate the little rosy-cheeked clerk told me "it's
            against the rules for new hands to stand here. You must go over by the stairs and wait
            till the forelady comes." I smiled at the pretty child and she rewarded me by bringing a
            chair to me a few minutes later. All means of communication being cut off I amused
            myself making sketches of the shirted, slippered, sleuth-like creature as he passed.
            This pastime was interrupted by the appearance of a fat woman. She had on a black sateen
            suit tha tfitted her puffy figure like the raiment of a well-boiled suet pudding. She
            carried herself like a drum-major on dress parade and by way of ornaments wore a gold
            watch with a double coil of gold chain at her belt, gold earrings, a gold breast pin,
            gold cuff-buttons, and two gold rings. Bigger than bust or bustle was the woman's head I
            discovered when Iasked: "Are you the forewoman?" "Forelady, yes. What do you want?"
            "Work" "What can you do?" "Sew." "Where have you been working?" "NeverRip company" "Want
            to stitch?" "No, I would rather finish." "Give your name to the clerk." I complied and
            was entered on his book as the resident of a vacant lot on Monroe street. The forewoman
            selected a bundle as big as a Kainschatka baby from a mountain of bundles and said:
            "Here, go over there and wait till I come." "How much do you pay for thi sclass of
            work?" "I don't know. It seems to me you're mighty particular." "If you don't know who
            does?" I asked. "You make me dizzy," she said, dropping the bundle and giving me a look
            of intense disgust. She took a small book from her pocket containing the price-list and
            asked me what number. "I don't know." "Look." "Where?" "You'll come down a peg or two
            before long," and with a groan she bent over the bundle at her feet, flushed
            apoplectically, and said "360." Referring again to her price-list: "Them's 65 cents,"
            and left me. I raised that 65-cent <unclear/> clusterand with my arms folded about the
            fuzzy, ill-smelling thing, moved "down there," as directed, and halted at the edge of a
            huge rag-box. Here I stood for twenty minutes, when the forewoman came aft and bade me
            "this way." I pursued. There was a halt about the middle of the shop and I seized it for
            a "scoop." "How many girls have you here?" "Never counted them." "What can experienced
            cloak hands earn a day?" "Never asked them." "How much of your salary is for
            politeness?" "You can sit here," pointing to a cane chair with half the seat gone. "That
            girl with the black dress will do your stitching, the one at the end of the second table
            will bind the seams, and Annie down there in the brown calico - she's fixing the machine
            now - will give you any help," and she was off. "I beg your pardon, did I understand you
            to say I would get 65 cents for making this cloak?" following her. "Now you're just a
            little too fresh. If you don't want the work, say so." "I do want the work, but I want
            to know what it will pay first." "This is a 65-cent cloak. Do you get that through your
            head? The stitcher gets 20 cents, the binder gets 15 cents, and you get 30 cents for
            finishing if the work is right. If it isn't, you get out." I thanked her and was alone.
            Here I thought lay my fortune. Thirty cents for making a long cloth cloak, after the
            seams were stitched. It had t obe trimmed down the back gores, around the collar, cuffs,
            and pockets with mohair plush: the sleeves had to go in, eighteen buttons sewed on,
            eighteen holes worked, and all the seams and edges faced with black muslin. Thirty
            cents! To save my life I couldn't have finished the garment in ten hours. I was just
            reaching that conclusion when the forewoman appeared with a small book, two checks, and
            a piece of tailor's chalk as big as a dime. "Your number is 180: chalk it on all these
            pieces and if you lose any you will be fined." "How much?" "How much? You cheeky thing!
            The cost of the cloth and the cutter's time. That's how much. Give this check to the
            binder and that one to the stitcher." "Will you please tell me how this side gore goes?"
            "Go to Annie. I ain't here to learn you how to sew." "May I have a needle?" "Furnish
            your own needles." "May I have basting cotton?" "There ain't any. You have to wait till
            it gets here." I gave a girl a penny for a needle and stole some thread from an
            absentee's stock. Then I waited fifteen minutes while the binder got through and basted
            up the scams for the stitcher. That much done I got to work on the plush. The forewoman
            passed by and told me I was not "showing" enough fur. Go over to the sample and look at
            the work." She sneered when I asked where the samples were, but a neighnor volunteered
            the information. There was no sample on the rack and I stepped over to inform the
            forewoman, who curtly told me it was none of her affair. "Will you please tell me how
            wide to make this trimming?" "Go to Annie." Poor Annie was doctoring a machine and said
            "in a minute." On her way to me three stitchers implored her to look at their miserable
            implements and I waited patiently till I caught sight of the forewoman looking at her
            bangs in a handglass. Apologizing for the intrusion I asked her if the sample had come
            yet. "No." "I wish you would kindly show me how wide to make this trimming." "Go to
            Annie, I told you." "Annie is too busy. She's mending machines." "Well, I won't be
            bothered with you?" "What's the reason you won't?" "Cause I won't." "Well you will. Tell
            me how wide you want this plush or I will see Mr. Ellinger." "See him. I don't care.
            There he is," pointing to the snaky, half-starved creature whose shanks I had been
            sketching and on whom I had scornfully turned my back. </articleBody>
    </div>


</root>
