<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="astronautsFloat.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<news>
    <head>
        <headLine>2 Astronauts Float Free in Space, 170 Miles Up</headLine>
        <image>
            <pic file="astroFloat.jpg"/>
            <caption><person ref="#McCandless_B">Capt. Bruce McCandless</person> 2d working outside
                the cargo bay of the shuttle.</caption>
        </image>
        <byLine>By <person ref="#Noble_J">John Noble</person></byLine>

        <info>Special to The New York Times</info>
        <dateLine><place>Houston</place><date when="1964-02-07">Feb. 7</date></dateLine>
    </head>
    <body>
        <p>-- In a spectacle of bravery and beauty, two American astronauts flew out, up and away
            from the space shuttle Challenger today. Free of any lifeline and propelled into the
            dark void by tiny jets, they became, in effect, the first human satellites.</p>

        <p>The successful test of the propulsion backpacks - a wireless high-wire act 170 miles
            above the earth - was an important step toward future operations to repair and service
            orbiting satellites and to assemble and maintain large space stations.</p>

        <p>A second test by the same two space fliers, <person ref="#McCandless_B">Capt. Bruce
                McCandless</person> 2d of the Navy and Lieut. Col. Robert L. Stewart of the Army, is
            scheduled for Thursday morning. They are to practice grappling a large object rotating
            at the end of the shuttle's mechanical arm, a dress rehearsal for a mission in April to
            repair a crippled scientific satellite.</p>

        <subHead>Success After Failures</subHead>

        <p>The success of today's space-walking exercise was particularly sweet for the National
            Aeronautics and Space Administration, coming as it did after days of repeated failures.
            Two satellites deployed by the shuttle went off-course, and a target balloon burst to
            disrupt another test for the satellite-repair mission.</p>

        <p>All that was forgotten when, at 8:25 A.M. Eastern standard time, <person
                ref="#McCandless_B">Captain McCandless</person> fired the jet thrusters of his bulky
            white backpack to rise out of the Challenger's open cargo bay and move away, untethered
            to the spaceship. He was orbiting the earth at the same velocity as the shuttle, 17,500
            miles an hour. In the virtual vacuum of space, however, he sensed nothing of his speed.
            The only sensation of motion he had came when he looked down at the rotating earth,
            which was going by at four miles a second.</p>
        <p> Beginning his excursion as the first free-flying human in space, <person
                ref="#McCandless_B">Captain McCandless</person> joked: ''That may have been one
            small step for Neil, but it's a heck of a big leap for me.''He was referring to the
            words uttered by Neil A. Armstrong when he made the first human bootprint on the moon in
            1969.</p>

        <p><person ref="#McCandless_B">Captain McCandless</person> took his big leap while the
            Challenger was passing over the Pacific Ocean, then in darkness. His movements were
            deliberate, never more than one foot a second. He said he looked for but could see no
            stars.</p>

        <p>He headed out to 150 feet, a stiff figure with slightly spread legs, looking a little
            like a puffy white gingerbread man. He then went out as far as 320 feet as he and the
            shuttle, separate but not too far apart, flew over the continental United States in
            daylight.</p>

        <p>''This is neat,'' he said. Then, casting an eye downward, he remarked: ''Looks like
            Florida. It is Florida!''</p>

        <p>'It Really Is Beautiful'</p>

        <p>He reported seeing clearly Cape Canaveral, where the mission began last Friday and where
            it is scheduled to end Saturday. ''It really is beautiful,'' Captain McCandless said of
            the panorama. By the time he returned to the shuttle, it was cruising over Africa. The
            astronaut had spent an hour and a half testing and flying the jet-powered backpack,
            known as the manned maneuvering unit. Except for a few minor ''shudders, rattles and
            shakes,'' which Captain McCandless noted in certain firings, the maneuvering unit's
            performance was smooth and all that the space agency had expected it to be. ''We sure
            have a nice flying machine here,'' he said. </p>

        <p>At all times, Captain McCandless and later Colonel Stewart were in sight of the
            Challenger, and the crew on board had them in their sights. Vance D. Brand, the
            commander, and Comdr. Robert L. Gibson of the Navy, the pilot, were ready, if necessary,
            to steer the shuttle over and scoop up the space fliers in the cargo bay. And Dr. Ronald
            E. McNair stood ready at the controls of the shuttle's 50-foot-long mechanical arm to
            use it to pluck one of the men back to safety.</p>
        <p> The need did not arise. John Cox, the flight director in the operations, said all the
            equipment ''seemed to work better than anyone hoped for.''</p>
        <p> At a news conference, Mr. Cox said, ''This was great confirmation that the plans made
            for the Solar Max repair all work perfectly.''</p>

        <p>Solar Max, formally known as the Solar Maximum Mission satellite, is the craft that
            astronauts wearing propulsion backpacks hope to retrieve and repair on the next shuttle
            flight, scheduled for early April. They plan to change defective electronics parts and,
            if this revives the malfunctioning systems, redeploy the satellite.</p>

        <p>Captain McCandless and Colonel Stewart worked for almost six hours, breathing oxygen from
            the smaller pack built into their pressure suits. While Captain McCandless was out
            flying, Colonel Stewart stepped into foot-restraints built into a metal plate that was
            attached to the end of the mechanical arm. He had some trouble fitting his boots under
            the metal toe bar and the into the metal heel cup.</p>

        <subHead>Disruption of Schedule</subHead>

        <p>This put him behind schedule, but he was able to perform some tasks working with tools
            that would come in handy making satellite repairs. In the absence of gravity, the
            foot-restraints kept him from being thrown into a spin or away from his task as he
            turned the wrenches or other devices. </p>
        <p>On future repair missions, astronauts expect to work in this way from the end of the
            mechanical arm, much as workers in orchards and on power lines use the so-called cherry
            pickers.</p>

        <p>Later in the morning, after Captain McCandless returned and the maneuvering backpack was
            refueled, Colonel Stewart got his chance to go overboard and fly. In about an hour's
            time, he duplicated most of the same maneuvers, going out as far as 305 feet.</p>
        <p> Returning to the shuttle, Colonel Stewart, a helicopter pilot before becoming an
            astronaut, commented, ''The approach to Challenger was a little different than the
            helicopter landings in Vietnam.''</p>
        <p> Captain McCandless, meanwhile, was taking his turn working from the end of the
            mechanical arm. ''O.K., Dr. McNair, throw the bolt,'' he radioed to the astronaut inside
            the cabin, Dr. Ronald E. McNair, who was operating the robotic arm.</p>

        <p>With his body extending straight out from the end of the arm, where his feet were fixed
            to the restraints, Captain McCandless sometimes evoked images of the wing-walkers of
            early aviation. But there was no breeze to flutter a silk scarf. And it was work he had
            in mind, not a frolic, as the shuttle passed over Baja California.</p>

        <p>The mechanical arm transported the astronaut within reach of a panel simulating the
            electronics modules that astronauts must replace on Solar Max. Captain McCandless
            practiced with tools to open, remove and replace those parts.</p>

        <p>''You going to want the windows washed or anything while I'm out here?'' he joked.</p>

        <subHead>Better Than Expected</subHead>

        <p>Mr. Cox, the flight director, said the tests indicated that the fully extended robotic
            arm provided a more stable work platform than had been expected. </p>
        <p>In one real repair, the astronauts adjusted the setting of a switch on a scientific
            instrument attached to a West German payload. This is the shuttle pallet satellite, a
            re-usable platform carrying instruments and cameras. It will serve as the object,
            attached to the mechanical arm, that Captain McCandless and Colonel Stewart are to hook
            up to in Thursday's planned space-walking activities.</p>

        <p>The astronauts also detached a malfunctioning television camera from the cargo bay,
            brought it in for repairs and plan to re-install it at the beginning of <event
                when="1964-06-24">Thursday's spacewalk</event>. The camera is expected to provide
            more television coverage of the astronauts as they grapple with the rotating pallet
            satellite at the end of the mechanical arm.</p>

        <p>The mishaps were few and minor. Captain McCandless dropped the checklist attached to his
            cuff and had to dump it into a small trash bag. And once, for reasons not quiet clear,
            he uttered an expletive of frustration, which proved that he was indeed a human
            satellite.</p>
        <p> As the two astronauts returned to the shuttle airlock, about 1 P.M., Captain McCandless
            said of the experience: ''It was a real thrill. A real honor to be out there.''</p>
    </body>
</news>
