<root>
                        MAKING TIDIES AT SIXTY CENTS A DOZEN AND PAYING THREE DOLLARS FOR THE PRIVILEGE.
                        A POOR GIRL WHO WORKED FROM JANUARY TO JULY TO MAKE FIFTEEN DOLLARS.

                        Tuesday, July 10, according to instructions from The Times,
                        I made up for the role of shop-girl, and with a list of factories
                        in one hand and gentle peace in the other sailed down State
                        street under a brown braize veil as impenetrable as an iron
                        mask. I applied at two feather factories and three corset shops,
                        but aside from the exercise up and down several flights of
                        stairs got nothing. The feather people did not need any help
                        and the corset folks had not started on the winter trade. I was
                        treated with civility, however, and given permission to "drop
                        in in a week or so." The fifth place on my list was a lace
                        manufacturing company on State street. Ascending one flight
                        of stairs I stopped to take off my veil, and adjust my eyes to
                        the low light. That done, I looked about and finding a door
                        marked "Office of the --- Lace Manufacturing Co." with
                        "Come in" on the glass I complied. A young girl followed
                        and leaving her to close the door I fell into a chair, the only
                        one about, and proceeded to perspire and scrutinize the place.
                        The office was not uninviting. The floor had a cheap carpet,
                        the ceiling was high and the room well ventilated and admirably
                        
                        lighted. On a long table that served as a sort of fortification
                        for the private office of the company were the samples -- "antique crocheted goods" -- as they are listed in various shades
                        of white. All were of different pattern and unvarying ugliness. There were round tidies and oblong tidies, square mats
                        for a bureau and smaller ones of oval and circular design,
                        intended for a lamp or cushion. Behind the table, sacheting
                        between a writing stand and a desk, was a young man of 30 or
                        so, of the blonde type, with a stationary scowl between his eyebrows and an otherwise pleasing manner. That is, I thought
                        the manner pleasing till I began to get acquainted with it and
                        then my opinion changed. After a lapse of five minutes or
                        so the fair-haired gentleman turned to the young girl with a
                        deepening of the scowl and a most unalluring "Well?"
                        "I brought the mats back."
                        "Oh, you have, eh?" opening a piece of newspaper and
                        unfolding a dozen hand-made mats the size of a tea-plate. The
                        work is carefully examined on both sides and as he proceeds
                        the scowl deepens, Without a word he tosses the lot on the
                        little table and reaches for the proffered blank the girl has
                        opened.
                        "What’s your name?"
                        "Rhafferty."
                        "How do you spell it?"
                        "R-h-a-f-f-e-r-t-y."
                        "Oh, yes; Martha Rhafferty," after hunting through a long
                        list.
                        "Do you want more work?"
                        "No, sir."
                        "There’s plenty more if you want it."
                        "No; my mother don’t want me to do any more crocheting."
                        "Well, Mr. White isn’t in now. Can’t you come in again?"
                        No answer. A look of discouragement comes over the
                        young face.
                        
                        "Don’t you have to do some shopping about town?"
                        "No, sir."
                        "Well, you can wait, can’t you? Wait here. Take a chair.
                        [I had the only one.] Just go in the next room there and take
                        a chair."
                        As he went to lead the way the crochet-teacher called his
                        attention, and the girl remaining I seized my chances for a bit
                        of interviewing.
                        Martha showed me her contract in which the firm had agreed
                        to refund $1 of the three deposited when she had finished $15
                        worth of work. On the back of the contract were the credit
                        receipts of the company entered in lead pencil, dating from
                        January to July. She told me she lived in Gross Park, away
                        out on the West Side; that she helped her mother, and had
                        been trying to earn $15 since January. She received 60 cents
                        a dozen for the mats and it took her a week to crochet a dozen.
                        "Then I must pay 10 cents car fare each time, and that
                        leaves me only 40 cents. I had to pay $3 before I could get
                        any work. I always knew how to crochet, but they made me
                        pay $2 for lessons and $1 as a security. I began in January,
                        the first week, and now I am through. I have made $15, and
                        when they give me back the dollar I shall have $16." Here is
                        a company paying a girl of 18 $15 for six months and one
                        week’s labor.
                        When Mr. F. came from the work-room he was met by a
                        boy who had brought in some work and was in a hurry to
                        be off.
                        "Mrs. C. sent in these mats and she wants you to receipt for
                        them."
                        The paper is opened and the work inspected. The scowl
                        deepens. There will be trouble and I prick up my ears.
                        "I don’t like this. This is bad. They are all stained.
                        Are you her -- her -- are you a relation?"
                        "Yes."
                        
                        "Well, you must tell her to wash her hands. These goods
                        are all sweat. I’ll have to charge her for spoiling the material if it occurs again. Did she tell you to ask for more work?"
                        "No, sir."
                        The poor boy is gone. Martha sits in the back room the
                        picture of suspense and the entry being made I am approached.
                        I look like a beggar and that is what I am taken for, as the
                        pretty blonde secretary only scowls. He stands and looks
                        down at me and I sit and look up at him waiting for the lines
                        in the handsome brow to deepen, the edge of the soft brown
                        mustache to curl, and the laconic, withering "well" to break
                        the daze. It comes.
                        "Have you any work?" I ask.
                        "Plenty. Do you want work?"
                        "Yes."
                        "What can you do?"
                        "Oh, I can crochet."
                        "This kind of work?" handing over one of the 60-cent
                        mats.
                        "Yes; what do you pay?"
                        "Different prices. Pay by the dozen, from 60 cents to $10."
                        "Let me have a dozen of the $10 kind, please, giving my
                        cat-colored eyes a mater voloroso sort of a roll. As he caught
                        the seraphic expression some facial machinery gave a lurch
                        that threw one side of his countenance bias for a second.
                        Reaching to the desk he pulled out the following circular and
                        handed it to me:
                        
                        Office of W---L--M----Co. (Incorporated,) S-- Street, Chicago, ILL. -- Madame: In reply to your letter regarding the work we send out to ladies to do at their homes we beg to say that we would make
                        a large line of crochet goods of our antique crochet cotton (a sample of which you will find enclosed), also linen, silk, etc. We make mats,
                        tidies, lambrequins, bedspreads, shams, collars, hoods, lace edging, etc., in large quantities.
                        
                        We have been established here for the last five years, and have extra
                        facilities for selling goods in large lots, so we are enabled to keep our workers in steady work all the time. Should you desire to work for us we should be pleased to send you work on the following terms:
                        When you send order for work you are required to remit to us $3; $2
                        of this is to pay us for the patterns and instructions which we shall send you with each lot of new work. (We shall also send you sufficient extra material so you can make a sample of each pattern sent, which you are allowed to keep for yourself); $1 of the $3 you send is a deposit on the material we send, and this we shall return to you at any time when you return the work and wish to stop. You will be kept in steady work, paid for each lot when made and returned to us in good order. Our work is all made by the dozen, and prices range from 50 cents per dozen to $10 per dozen, according to amount of work. An easy pattern with sample and full instructions will be sent you at first, and the quality of work, and advance in prices as you adapt yourself to doing it. The work will be sent you by mail, postage paid by us one way. Three month’s time is allowed you to do any one dozen of articles we send. This enables ladies who have only a few hours daily to spare to do our work as well as those
                        ladies who take it intending to do it steadily.
                        We are asked many times how much a lady can earn. This depends
                        entirely upon your ability to crochet and the time you have at your command daily; ladies earning from $2 to $5 weekly. We could not guarantee to anyone any stated amount that they could earn, but our work is easy, and after you accustom yourself to it you can do it yery rapidly.
                        If you desire to work for us fill out the blank below and return it to us with the $3, and we will place your name on our books and send work at once with full instructions. Send money by postoffice order, draft, payable to our order, or registered letter at our risk.
                        Very truly,	
                        -----
                        Keep the above for reference.
                        
                        W---L--M----Co., S-- Street, Chicago, ILL. - Gentlemen:
                        Inclosed find $3 that I send you to secure patterns, instructions, and material for crochet work; $2 is to pay you for samples and instructions, and $1 is for deposit on material which I shall demand returned to me at any time when I return to you the material in my hands.
                        Signature..................
                        Town....................
                        County...................
                        Street and No. ..............
                        
                        "What’s the $3 for?" I ask.
                        "Can’t you read? The $2 is to pay for the samples and instruction and the $1 as a security for our material. I don’t
                        know who you are and if I gave you the thread I might never
                        see you again."
                        "I don’t need instruction. I can make the stitch and I don’t
                        want to put any such amount in samples. If you can’t trust
                        me with a spool of thread and a pattern will you sell me the
                        material?"
                        "That’s not the way we do business. If you want to work
                        for us you must comply with the contract. You pay $3; that
                        entitles you to a sample mat which we teach you how to make.
                        After you have $15 made worth of work we refund the $1."
                        "What about the other $2?"
                        "It goes to us for instruction and samples."
                        "Will I have to make the samples?"
                        "Yes."
                        "Then there are thirteen in the lace manufacturing company’s dozen? "
                        "If you want to put it that way, yes. But you get one of
                        each set."
                        "But I don’t want any. I have a supply. Tell me how
                        much will you sell me a thirteenth of a dozen of this set for?"
                        "The price is on the tag."
                        "Ah, I see, 15 cents; and you pay 60 centsa dozen for making them, a profit of $1.20. The best thing I’ve struck yet.
                        Any stock for sale?"
                        The scowl becomes threatening, but I venture to ask how
                        much thread it takes to a mat for a closer calculation of the
                        profits.
                        No answer is deigned.
                        "If I give you $3 you will give me work?"
                        " Yes," in a sullen tone.
                        "How much?"
                        
                        "All you can do," brightning up a little.
                        "How do I know you will give me back $1 after I’ve earned
                        $15?" I ask. ‘‘I don’t know anything about you; I never
                        heard about your firm before, and there is no name on this
                        paper."
                        "I guess your motives are bad. You don’t want work."
                        "What guarantee have you to offer of honesty or respectability?"
                        With glaring eyes, distended nostrils, and face crimson with
                        rage he threw down a pile of 2-cent blank books in front of
                        me. "There’s our customers; every state in the union is rep-
                        resented; go to them if you want references. Here are more,
                        too," slaming down a sheet of paper with the names and Chi-
                        cago addresses of about forty women.
                        "I see you have a minimum local trade. Chicago women
                        don’t seem overzealous about the crocheting business." Then
                        I asked him where he got a market for the goods, and the
                        name of some business man to whom I could go for reference.
                        "Now I am not going to do any more talking with you
                        about this business."
                        ‘‘Why? Is it a secret organization, a sort of Masonic---"
                        "No, it isn’t secret or Masonic, but I don’t believe you’re
                        all right and I won’t answer any more questions until I know
                        who you are and what you want."
                        Poor Mr. F. was so furious by this time that I thanked him
                        for his attention and bade him good afternoon.
                        At the foot of the stairs I waited to tie my veil on and see
                        how Martha fared, but at the expiration of thirty minutes she
                        was still waiting for Mr. W. and her $16.
                        Of the five women I interrogated none of them were able to
                        earn 20 cents a day All expressed a liking for the work but
                        complained bitterly of the way the concern gave out the work.
                        For instance, bedspreads paid $10 a dozen, but not more than
                        three spreads were given to a hand and one of these was the
                        
                        sample. The little table-mats paid 50 cents per dozen, but
                        before a girl was able to crochet enough to live on she was
                        obliged to take collars made of fine thread in such an intricate
                        pattern that it was an utter impossibility to earn $1 a month.
                        No woman seen had earned $15 in less than six months, and
                        one of the most skilled hands had been on a 60-cent lot since
                        June 3.
                        By inquiry I learned that many women paid $3 and gave up
                        the work when they saw that it was not possible to make the
                        $15 necessary for the rebate. This fact does not appear in the
                        circulars, and it is not till after the contract has been signed
                        that the equivocal tactics of the concern are understood. Several cases are on record at the Woman’s Protective Agency, but
                        no judgment has been obtained, as the agreement stands valid
                        before the law. All that can be done in the matter is to warn
                        the public against a concern legally incorporated to grind the
                        life out of the women and girls unfortunate enough to patronize it.
</root>